<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Popular errors, in generall poynts concerning the knowledge of religion having relation to their causes, and reduced into divers observations / by Jean D'Espaigne.</title>
            <title>Erreurs populaires es poincts généraux, qui concernent l'intelligence de la religion. English</title>
            <author>Espagne, Jean d', 1591-1659.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 233 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 116 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A38612</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3267</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3075</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11788686</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11788686</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49144</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A38612)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49144)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 491:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Popular errors, in generall poynts concerning the knowledge of religion having relation to their causes, and reduced into divers observations / by Jean D'Espaigne.</title>
                  <title>Erreurs populaires es poincts généraux, qui concernent l'intelligence de la religion. English</title>
                  <author>Espagne, Jean d', 1591-1659.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 222 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Whittaker,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of Les erreurs populaires es poincts généraux, qui concernent l'intelligence de la religion.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christianity --  Philosophy.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49144:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>POPVLAR ERRORS, IN Generall Poynts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the knowledge of RELIGION: Having Relation to their cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and reduced into divers obſervations.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> Jean D'Eſpaigne, <hi>Miniſter of the Holy Goſpell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for THO. WHITTAKER, at the ſigne of the Kings armes in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1648.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:49144:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49144:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of crowned double rose</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of crowned thistle</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of crowned celtic harp</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <head>To the moſt Illuſtrious <hi>CHARLES,</hi> Monarch of great <hi>Brittaine,</hi> &amp;c. Defender of the Faith.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He deceaſed King, Father of your Majeſty, was pleaſed to command the impreſſion of a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuſcript which was the firſt fruits of my Pen, on which hee
<pb facs="tcp:49144:3"/>daigned to caſt his eyes; where in his Royall goodneſſe had more reſpect to my zeale, then to the worke. This which I offer at your Majeſties feet, carries its deniall on the front. But that the clemencie of him who was pleaſed to caſt his eye upon the Hyſop, as well as upon the Cedars of <hi>Lebanon,</hi> makes me hope for a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable Aſpect. I beſeech the Lord God to accept your oblations, and make your Crowne flouriſh, and eſtabliſh your Throne as the Sun it ſelfe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:49144:3"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Treatiſe is nothing but a heape of obſervations very differing there, more eſpecially where they are joyned; they are for the moſt part diſtant in reſpect of the ſubject. This is the reaſon wherefore I have only ſought to range them in their proper places, and paſse from the one unto the other, without giving them any other connexion, or cloſing them with other cimment. I ſhall marke in the firſt place the nature and differencie of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, principally of the common people in matters concerning Religion; Secondly, the matters which are of the knowledge thereof. Thirdly, the forme and manner of this know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and finally the meanes to obtaine it. In all theſe foure heads (which I have pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in as many ſections) wee ſhall ſhew di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers popular errors which ſerve for the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of this Treatiſe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:49144:4"/>
            <p>If this worke be triviall, it correſponds to its title, which promiſeth nothing but popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar matters, if defective, 'tis for having o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted that which many have often repeated; if clowniſh, this ſtuffe is not capable of a more artificiall web, nor of the poliſure of a more elegant ſtile; if raſh, as ſhocking ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny maximes held as Oracles among the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and partly approved by the ſilence of the learned; weighing them in the ballance of the Sanctuarie, we ſhall find that in matter of Religion, nothing ought to be more ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted then vulgar opinions; ſome think to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand very well their religion that will find themſelves not only in a darke ignorance, but alſo in a den of Errors.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="section">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49144:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The firſt Section.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER I. <hi>The firſt Errour which aroſe amongſt Chriſtians.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He report which was ſpread a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Diſciples of the Lord, a few dayes before his Aſcenſion, that St. <hi>John</hi> the Evangeliſt ſhould not die, was the firſt Errour that ſprang up amongſt the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians. This opinion contradicted not any article of the Faith: and nevertheleſſe the Spirit of truth would have the cenſure thereof to remaine till the end of dayes, as a Pillar of Salt to ſeaſon our conceptions. Each Errour in things indifferent, is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:49144:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>of a Chriſtian. Time hath refuted many, if antiquity ſhould again ariſe ſhe would be aſhamed to have marked with Hereſie, thoſe who believed the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tipodes, and the Scholaſticks who tooke <hi>Zona torrida</hi> for the flaming ſword which made the earthly Paradice unacceſſible, they would find at this day theſe imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions were more ſpecious then veritable.</p>
               <p>But I will lay aſide all matters of this quality, we conteſt not here the common opinion which marks the nativity of our Saviour to be in the ſeaſon of the winter Solſtice, nor the oracles attributed to the Sybills, which if we muſt believe all that they ſay, have ſpoken of Jeſus Chriſt more clearely upon the Tripos of Idols then the true Prophets upon the ſeat of Truth. Nor the hiſtories which contain ſo many particularities of <hi>Simon Magus</hi> which are for the moſt part fables. Nor the interpretation which takes the foure living creatures deſcribed in <hi>Daniel</hi> for the foure Evangeliſts. Nor the forme which they attribute to the croſſe, which
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:49144:5"/>many ſay to have been of another faſhion then they repreſent at this day. Nor the belief that <hi>Adam</hi> &amp; the men of the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent world were of giant-like ſtature, theſe are problems we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ouch not, much leſſe will I ſpeak of opinions of which you may put amongſt the dorages of old womens tales, or that the Hebrew or any other tongue be naturall, or that there hath been men ingeudeed by devills, or whether witches can transform themſelves into wolves or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other ſpecies. There is none but ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Idiots who believe Luciſer to be the name of the devill. And many ſay the tree of the croſse without thinking on the ſuperſtition, which hath produced this fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion of ſpeech, imagining that the croſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> on which our Saviour ſuffer'd was made o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the wood of the tree of life. The opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which I undertake to refuſe are of far greater conſequence, they concern the true intelligence of Religion, in ſtead of which many embrace an ignorance reduced into art ſuſtained by maximes, which under appearance of follid piety do infold di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49144:6"/>capitall errors, transforming men into ſtones, making ſuperfluous the greateſt part of the Scripture, and inſtead of Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rubins engrave upon the walls the figure of many unclean creeping things; of theſe maximes ſome are avowed by an expreſſe profeſſion, others tacitely authorized by the common practiſe, not onely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the dregs of the people, but yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt many which are not ſeparated fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ignorants, but by the wainſcot of a pulpit.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>Of the efficacy and differencie of humours up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the intelligency of Religion and of the ſtrange opinions they produce.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Hold there are very few men alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether exempt from popular errors; the ſpirits the moſt pure have ſtill a touch in ſome point of this contagion. The reaſon is, that man naturally ſeeks to conceive the truth of things, the neareſt to the form of his own inclination, as he that would turn the courſe of his boul, turns his head on that ſide, to this contributes edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49144:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>old cuſtoms, and the multitude of voices, which ſtupifies the ſtrongeſt brains. Now as the inclinations are different, the truth which is unick in it ſelf appeares in divers forms, according to the quality of the ſpirits, which conceives it, like the <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiopians</hi> repreſenting the uglineſſe of the devill, have a cuſtome contrary to other people, they paint him white; ſo after this manner the diverſity of humours pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces diverſity of conceptions and diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of opinions upon the ſame ſubject.</p>
               <p>Theſe humours ſome times carries away mens ſpirits to make them ſeek to be more perfect then God himſelf, ſome cannot perſwade themſelves that God is ſo ſevere as he ſaith himſelf to be, and being touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with an humour more pitifull, have found wherewithall to extinguiſh the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall fire, teaching that the damned, nay more, that the devills after ſome time of ſuffering, in the end ſhall be freed from their torments; this ſo favorable an opinion hath gotten them the title of mercifull Doctors, but there is others who being of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49144:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>a more cholerick religion, would be more rigorous towards ſinners then God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. For if ſome man through humane frailty have faln under the burden of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, and ſince raiſed from his fall, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired the peace of the church, theſe would refuſe it him, although he had ſought it w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> tears of blood; as if they had had more intereſt in the offence, then God himſelf, or Jeſus Chriſt who dyed for that ſinner. Our Lord hath ſaid, if you are perſecuted in one place flie into another, ſome ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abounding in zeal have judged the practice of this command to be unworthy a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian generoſity, nay more, a baſe coward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe equivolent to a diſſertion of the faith, one of the chief writers of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Church hath ſet out a Treatiſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly in favour of this Paradox. The me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholie humour ſo farre predominates in many, that their piety conſiſts in ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe taking the wrinkles of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head for marks of Religion, and ſcarce will they believe him to be a good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian that is not Hypocondriacall: Men
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49144:7"/>the moſt pious have alwayes been different in their faſhion of life: ſome ſociable and Politicke, others loving a retired life with faſting and auſterity, to theſe two ſorts of humours, which are the moſt generall (God himſelfe by a wiſe indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence) would deferre ſomething, to the end, to draw all ſorts of people to his Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell; making them ſee two different Mod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels, The one in <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> a man of great abſtinencie and auſteritie, as well in life as in cloathing; the other in Jeſus Chriſt, whoſe life was popular, and diſdained not the table, nor converſation of the greateſt ſinners. But this could not univerſally pleaſe all men. The ſpotts which appeare in the writings of the cleareſt authors ſhew oft-times the humour in which they dipt their Pen, which you may perceive among many others in S. <hi>Jerome.</hi> Now theſe irregular impreſſions which nature formes in their ſpirits, goes not alwayes to ſo remarkable an exceſſe. But although a man be exempt from all groſſe, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table errors; nevertheleſſe thoſe truths
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49144:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>which are lodged in his ſpirit have ſome taint of his owne humor; And there is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry few men but that give unto religion ſome face or colour, or ſome poſture ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their particular inclination. And if one might looke into their braines, you ſhould ſee as many ſeverall Ideas as you doe of faces.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>Naturall humours taken for Chriſtian ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues: and the particular ſpirit, for the Spirit of the holy Ghoſt: The divell falſly accuſed of all our evill thoughts: why it is hard for a man to know the time when he was regenerated, why certaine articles of our faith are more eaſie to our beliefe then others: why divine Revelations were communicated to men in their ſleepe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THeſe naturall qualities oft-times de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the cleareſt ſights: the mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration which you ſee in many, proceeds rather from the heavineſſe of their flegme,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49144:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>then from a vertuous habitude; many are ardent in religion, and believe they have the Zeale of God, who if entireing into themſelves, would find that the fire which hears them, proceeds from a naturall choler, farre different from true zeale; many take the combat of the conſcience, for that of the ſpirit againſt the fleſh, and ſecurity for the Peace of conſcience. Many alſo are religious through a fearfull humour, proceeding either from the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the ſex, or the imbecillity of a ſcrupulous ſpirit, in things the moſt indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent, making as much eſteeme of an arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of Diſcipline, as of an article of Faith, and flying ſuperſtition, through a ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious feare.</p>
               <p>There are ſome found, that are ſo adi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to meditation, that they almoſt fall into an extaſie, ſo fervent and aſſiduall in prayers, that they diſdaine to deſcend from the Mountaine with <hi>Moſes,</hi> or from the third Heaven with S. <hi>Paul,</hi> for to return to converſe with men: ſome aſſure them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of their conſtancie in the faith, upon
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49144:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>a naturall generoſity, the experience whereof diſcovers its weakneſſe, making the moſt reſolute co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ages to abjure at the voyce of a Maid, and teacheth us that mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdome is a thing that man cannot pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to God; In generall a Chriſtian ought to keepe himſelfe from being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by theſe naturall qualities; like the Comets which have the forme and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of Starres, but yet are not fixed in the firmament.</p>
               <p>There raignes two falſe opinions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt thoſe which are ignorant, upon this ſubject; that all the ill thoughts and wicked and blaſphemous imaginations which paſſe through their braines againſt their will, proceeds from another ſpirit then their own, and accuſe the divell there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; which ought to be true in part, but I believe often-times they doe him wrong, for although there ſhould have been no di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels, the ſpirit of man is ſufficiently fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in monſtrous abſurdities for to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce ſuch fancies, without the ſuggeſtion of evill angels; and 'tis not to be believed
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49144:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>that Satan hath leave to enter ſo freely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all houſes, or to enter into our Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers and Cabinets whenſoever he pleaſes, much leſſe into our thoughts.</p>
               <p>There is another familiar errour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to many which take their incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, who have ſome morall goodneſſe for an infallible marke of the Spirit of grace; of all thoſe who have ſome light fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of religion there is not one but doth believe, that he is already regenerated. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all becauſe they cannot remember the time in which they have perceived ſo notable a motion, they preſuppoſe they have been regenerated in their infancie, not having any other memorie thereof. And indeed it is very difficult for a man to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the true moment of his converſion, in punctually noting the houre or the day. We perceive not how it is made in us in its firſt moment, nor haue we any hand there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, no more then in our naturall producti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: If a dead man ſhould ariſe he could not tell how he recovered life. Nay more, this regeneration is not wrought by a vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49144:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>and remarkable motion, except in ſome one, as it was in <hi>Paul,</hi> as in thoſe who in the ſame houre from tormentors became Martyrs, and as without doubt it comes to paſſe in ſome whom God regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates at the brinke of the ſepulchre. Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily the Spirit of God leads men inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly to the firſt point of Sanctification, by many turnings and preceding diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which in their beginnings are not to be perceived, but many make themſelves believe they have been regenerated from their cradle, which are as yet far from the ſtate of grace.</p>
               <p>Nay, thoſe, namely who have been a long time regenerated, and have gotten a ſollid experience in ſpirituall things, find themſelves oft-times deceived by their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular ſpirit, which counterfeits the voyce of the Spirit of God. Theſe two ſpirits intermingle themſelves in many actions. It was by the Spirit of God that <hi>Iſaac</hi> bleſſed <hi>Jacob,</hi> but in this, that he believed that he bleſt <hi>Eſau,</hi> and ſuch was his intention, it was the errour of his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:49144:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſpirit. It was by the Spirit of God that certaine Prophets told <hi>Paul,</hi> that bonds did attend him at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> but the counſell they gave him not to goe thither, was a motion of their owne particular ſpirit, proceeding from their humane af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. All the dreames which came to the Prophets were not propheticall, they had markes by which they diſcerned the celeſtiall viſions from naturall impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to which they were ſubject as well as other men; In the ſame manner as the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine providence of God hath ſeparated that which was writ by their particular motion, from that which was tranſmitted unto us by divine inſpiration; The Spirit which dictated the letter of <hi>David,</hi> writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with the bloud of poore <hi>Uria,</hi> was quite contrary to that which indited the Pſalmes. <hi>Nathan</hi> counſelling the build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Temple, ſeemed, ſpeaking like a godly man, but the conſequence ſhewes he ſpake not like a Prophet.</p>
               <p>It is moſt true, that neither ſagacity nor humane affections reduced into a juſt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49144:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>temper are not incompatible with ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all wiſdome, contrarily they ſerve for a helpe to our weakneſſe: All the articles of our faith are equally true, but our beliefe embraces them not with equall facility. We have leſſe trouble to believe a divine Eſſence, then a Trinity of Perſons: the immortality of the ſoule, then the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the body; The reaſon is, that in the one we have nothing but a ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall revelation for the ground of our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe; and in the other we are moreover ſuſtained by humane reaſon, which ſtrengthens this faith: So our obedience is more voluntary in things to which wee have, beſides the commandement of God, ſome naturall or perſonall inclination, then in thoſe which are repugnant to our affections: I doubt not but <hi>Abraham</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed more joyfully, when it was bidden him not to lay his hand upon <hi>Iſaac;</hi> then when he was commanded to ſlay him. But in this concurrence, namely of the Spirit of God with our ſpirits, wee muſt marke theſe two principalls, the one of which is
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49144:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>alwaies regular, and the other hath ſtill ſome ſpice of obliquity.</p>
               <p>A man addicted to his ſence, and that adores his owne opinions will very hardly give place to the Spirit of God. Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily Prophecies and Revelations came un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to men then, when they were aſleep; where God ſent them thoſe extaſies, whilſt they laſted they were as if deprived of all ſence, which was becauſe the ſoule is then diſ-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangled from many functions, and freed from an infinity of thoughts and of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects which poſſeſſed it waking; being then leſſe glued to their naturall judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſo more ſuſceptible of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluencie of heaven, and more capable to receive the impreſſion thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:49144:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>CHAP. IIII. <hi>Concerning the Sences: and of the imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: vulgar meditations: matters which ſeeme better in Painting, then in the words of the holy Scripture. Why the corporall figure of our Saviour is not delineated in the Goſpell: Why the ſight of the places (eſteemed holy) takes away the admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>REligion contains divers matters which for a ſimple hiſtoricall knowledge are intelligible to the externall ſenſes: The ſtarre which appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the wiſe men: the manger at <hi>Beth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lehem,</hi> the crown of Thornes, the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Croſse, the Sepulchre of Chriſt, and his comming out thereof; the ſcarres of his Wounds, his Aſcenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to Heaven, are objects perceptible to the imagination: Nay, we cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the truth of the naturall body of Chriſt, but under an imaginable and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible forme. But the internall forme of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:49144:12"/>all theſe theologicall truths which is as it were the ſoul of Religion, is not apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible but to the intellect. The divinity re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident in Chriſt; the perſonall union of the two Natures, the merits of his Death, the efficacie of his Interceſſion, the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of the juſtice of God in this ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; The eternall Election, the interiour Vocation, Juſtification, the eſſence of the Faith, the regeneration, are matters pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intellectuall. In every narration, prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally in each article of faith which lies in the Hiſtorie, there is ever two things re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite to the intelligence thereof; 1. The action with its circumſtances; Secondly, the cauſes and the conſequences thereof. Now the firſt point is better ſtudied, and more ſought into by the common people, as being more delectable to the imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and far eaſier to bee conceived then the other, which touches not the ſenſes, and requires a more ſpirituall, and more laborious exerciſe of the underſtanding; from whence it comes to paſſe, that the ſcience, the conception, the proofes and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49144:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>meditations of the vulgar are more ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginative then intellectuall. A Deaths head, the ſpectacle of a carkaſſe, or of a dying man will repreſent our humane fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gility more lively then can doe all the ſentences of the Bible. But the ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall cauſes of this corruption, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences thereof from whence reſults the true intelligence of our mortality, they are not read in ſuch characters: A picture may give knowledge of an action, but the reaſons and the motives in which lyes the importance of the ſtory askes another Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſill. A Crucifix tells us not why Jeſus Chriſt died. Never man was yet conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the ſight of a picture. If that were, Painters and Sculptors would be the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Theologians. After the ſame manner the ſufferings of Chriſt reduced into a Tragedy, and elevated by the higheſt co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours of Eloquence, what teares ſoever it may draw from the auditors, will never ſuffice for a ſaving knowledge.</p>
               <p>If the true pourtraict of Jeſus Chriſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting his naturall face, were to be
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:49144:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>found in the world, I would never blame the curioſity of thoſe who would ſeek the poſſeſſion, and who (all ſuperſtition ſet apart) would preſerve it as one of the moſt precious jewels that the eye of man can behold. Many have thought, that they have the originall, in an Epiſtle of <hi>Len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulus</hi> to the Senate of <hi>Rome,</hi> of which I will ſay no more, but that it is no Roman ſtile; Some others have drawne the Copy from the Monument of a fabulous hiſtory which ſpeaks of a Statue erected in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of our Saviour.</p>
               <p>Howſoever it comes to paſſe, it is a ſtrange thing that the Scripture which paints forth the ſtature of <hi>Saul,</hi> the haire of <hi>Abſalom,</hi> the colour and viſage of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> expreſſes not any figure of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our. We find not therein the leaſt Idea, nor any lineament, neither of his face, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, aſpect, ſtature, or yet of his voyce. But that by which he was diſcernable from other men, conſiſted not in his viſible forme, or in any extraordinary difference of Lineaments, otherwiſe <hi>Judas</hi> had not
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49144:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>needed a ſigne to make him to be known; ſo that the repreſentation of him at this day to the eye of fleſh, would make him contemptible to him that would not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a divine Majeſty under a common and indifferent appearance. Or it would be a Patron of Idolatry, which would not faile to multiply under ſo favourable a pretext. Our humane vanity would have added there to ſome frivolous and imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent ſpeculations of Phiſiognomie. Or ſuperſtition would caſt its ſight upon each man who ſhould have ſome ſeeming re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance of ſuch a Picture. Or certainly the greateſt part of Chriſtians in ſtead of knowing Chriſt in ſpirit, and adoring him ſpiritually, would alwayes have his ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination tied to the corporall object, and his ſpirit diſturbed with the fancy thereof.</p>
               <p>Of thouſands of men who returne from <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> or from mount <hi>Sina,</hi> or from the river of <hi>Jordan,</hi> and many other famous places mentioned in the Scripture, ſcarce can you find one which brings back the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration, which he had conceived before
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:49144:14"/>he had ſeen them. The ſpirit of man hath alwayes a more reverent opinion of things which are ancient, then of Moderne: of thoſe which are fartheſt off, then of thoſe which are neare. The objects, the moſt excellent and ſacred become contemptible by the facility and proximity of acceſſe: but thoſe who goe out of a devout affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to viſite <hi>Paleſtine</hi> or <hi>Arabia,</hi> carry with them for the moſt part exorbitant imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations which ſometimes paſſe to an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe impoſſible in nature, thinking to find the third heaven in a cave, not conſidering that the innobling of thoſe places, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds not from any quality which renders them either more holy, or more full of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty then the other parts of the earth, but from the ſole reputation of the wonders paſt under that climate, ſo that the ſight takes away the eſteeme thereof, becauſe it anſwers not to the imaginations with which they were preoccupied.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:49144:15"/>
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Of the difference and capacity of ſpirits: Of the faculties of the ſoule: Of thoſe who promiſe themſelves to beleeve, ſo that they have proofe, and doe aſſure themſelves they ſhould have beleeved in Chriſt, if they had ſeene his Miracles; Of thoſe who li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit God, according to their owne wiſdome, or beleeve the truth, becauſe it is confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable to their owne opinion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TO diſpute whether there bee Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits more capable of Theologie then others, or whether the facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the ſoule are prevalent in this ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, are queſtions remore from our intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; without controverſie the intellect is the true place of this ſcience, although the vulgar imagine that there is more trouble to retaine a point of Religion, then to conceive it, and wiſh rather the gift of memorie, then that of the underſtanding.</p>
               <p>The knowledge of ſalvation is an effect of grace only. A ſingle, hiſtoricall, and ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culative
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49144:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>culative knowledge proceeds from a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular favour of God. But this grace de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyes neither the naturall difference nor eſſence of ſpirits. God employes for our inſtruction, the objects, the ſences, and the other faculties of the ſoule. Jeſus Chriſt himſelfe as hee was man became more knowing by experience; a man which hath the ſence of hearing, from whence comes faith, hath a manifeſt advantage for the underſtanding of preaching, above that man whom God hath ſtrucken with deaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; ſo there is no doubt but a good na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall underſtanding (preſuppoſing the light of grace) knowes better how to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a matter of religion, and to weigh the importance thereof, and ſearch into the cauſes, and to diſcover the conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, then a ſpirit naturally ſtupid, and blockiſh; the greateſt braines are ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily more ſlow to believe, then thoſe which have but mean ones, as the higheſt Planets have the ſloweſt motions, but their beliefe is more ſollid, when once they have known the truth; For God employes the ſame
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49144:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>faculties for to produce an effect for which they had nothing but a naturall repugnan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie: ſo that the moſt violent perſecutors become oft-times the greateſt zelots of the faith: whether the faculty of thoſe who believe more promptly be more wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of praiſe, it's a point we will not as yet touch. The vulgar preſuppoſe that the Science of religion requires nothing but a ſingle apprehenſion or reception of truths preſuppoſed without any mixtion of the diſcurſive faculty, and without any act of the judgement: many make ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of reaſoning upon the doctrines o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> faith, becauſe that reaſon is nothing but a naturall faculty. But this maxime in the ſence they give unto it is in effect contrary to all reaſon: by the ſame conſequence they ought not to bring to Church, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their eares nor common ſence for to diſcerne the voyce and accents of the Word which is preached unto them, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their memorie to retaine the impreſſion for theſe faculties, as well as reaſon ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> purely naturall. I will leave what is to be
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:49144:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſpoken upon this ſubject to come to ſome remarkes. Scarce can a man bee found doubting of ſome point of religion, but he promiſeth himſelfe firmly to beleeve the truth, ſo that hee may ſee manifeſt and concluding proofe, there is nothing ſo common as this voyce. If I ſee the proofe, I will believe it: But they promiſe that which is not in their power: for every hiſtoricall faith it ſelfe is a gift of God: and ſaving faith proceeds from a particular favour of heaven. In the meane time they attribute unto themſelves the power, thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king that the matters of the faith may as eaſily be inſinuated into our beliefe as philoſophical propoſitions, which have no need but of a moral perſwaſions, or of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of the ſenſes for to introduce them into our ſpirit: Whereas theologicall truths, the moſt cleare and palpable, are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies obſcure unto us without a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar illumination.</p>
               <p>With a like vanity many aſſure them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that if they had ſeene the miracles that God wrought in <hi>Egypt,</hi> or that Jeſus
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:49144:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>Chriſt did in <hi>Judea,</hi> they would not have failed to believe in him. They wonder at the ſtupidity of the Jewes, and thinke that if ſuch wonders had been preſented to their eyes they ſhould have been far from being incredulous: But certainly if a man ſhould ſee all the rivers converted into blood, the Seas cleave in ſunder, the Heaven open his gates, the Mountaines to remove them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, the Sun ſtand ſtill, the Dead to come forth of their graves, the Rocks to melt into water, when he himſelfe ſhould have been in Heaven, or ſhould have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned from Hell, he would not have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned better if God gave him not ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther underſtanding capable of this faith.</p>
               <p>Now the Idolatrie which formes God after the reſemblance of man, conſiſts not alwayes in Statues or materiall pictures, neither in the groſſe conception of Ideots who never thinke of God, but in imagin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome figure apprehenſible to the ſence, and place in Heaven a fantaſme for the object of their contemplation. But there is one far more ſubtill, which indeed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiders
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:49144:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>God as a Spirit, but bounds him by the law of Nature, or reſtraines him to the ſame lawes which ſerve for bounds to the humane ſpirit, or confines his wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to the maximes of morall and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectuall vertues.</p>
               <p>Two things amongſt all others, have ſeemed moſt abſurd in the true religion, the one under the Ancient teſtament, to wit, the Circumciſion, the other under the New, to wit, the Croſſe of Chriſt, the one ordained for a Sacrament, the other for the foundation properly of the Alliance both of them ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in themſelves, ridiculous in the quality the Scripture gives them. For God would oblige the wiſeſt to ſearch their ſalvation by a way that ſhould be ſcandalous to naturall prudence, to the end that their wiſdome ſhould not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake to controule his, which never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe happens without thinking there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the moſt religious ſpirits. The anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Chriſtians in their ordinary prayers demanded of God the retarding of the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:49144:18"/>laſt day. This requeſt was founded upon the comming of Antichriſt, which they knew ought to preceed that day, which would bring with it many calamities, which they ſought to keep from them by their praſers upon this, that the Aſſemb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the Elect, and the calling of ſo many people, would require a long ſpace of time, and upon other reaſons which was knowne unto them, but they tooke not heed that the holy Ghoſt, whoſe fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight ſurpaſſes that of man, commanded them to ſay, <hi>Come Lord Jeſus, come.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For a cloſe, we ſhall marke that in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers matters of religion many ſubmit their beliefe to the teſtimony of the Scripture, becauſe that they find therein ſome rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or circumſtance, which ſeemes to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree with their naturall judgement. They perſwade themſelves of the truth of an hiſtory, or the equity of a law, or the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie of a myſtery, or the importance of a Sacrament, or the juſtice of a rigorous execution, for as much as they meet there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a certaine ſhadow, or an appearance
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:49144:18"/>conformable to the thoughts which are the moſt prevalent in their ſpirits, the faith proceeding thereof is vaine: as wee ſhall declare hereafter in its proper place.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Some ſay Knowledge produceth Atheiſme, all here ſaies have not proceeded from lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men. The abuſes of humane learning in religion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe common people reproches A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thieſme to the learned, and their ſcorning of all religion. An ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation, but too true in reſpect of many. Some doe ſo incloſe themſelves within the thoughts of a Science, or particular fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, that their ſpirit cannot admit any principall higher then that of their owne art, from whence it comes to paſſe, that they know no other divinity then the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and the forme, or the temperature of the body, or the vertue of herbs; or the law of nature, or nature it ſelfe. Others
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:49144:19"/>although moſt ſpeculative in the higher cauſes attaine not to the firſt.</p>
               <p>But certainly we muſt impute this crime to their ignorance, not to their know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; for to ſay the truth, there was never Atheiſt, but was ignorant: never a perfect Philoſopher, but acknowledged a God, the moſt ſpecious arguments that impiety euer diſplayed for to ſight againſt this fundamentall point of religion, if we look neerly unto it, are nothing but popular reaſons. And it is impoſſible to an Atheiſt to ſuſtain his cauſe without diſavowing ſome principalls of naturall reaſon. If A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſme were grounded upon knowledge, the perſwaſion would be the ſtronger in ſtead that its weakneſſe is ſubject to a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand doubts, which wearies thoſe which are moſt obſtinate; As I have ſeene in a learned man famous in his profeſſion, who having called my ſelfe to comfort him in his ſickneſſe, aſſured me upon the (ſilence he exacted of me) that his health depended upon the reſolution of a point which he never could believe, and asked the proofe
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:49144:19"/>thereof, which was, if there were a God, a queſtion ſo criminall, that cannot proceed but from a ſpirit full of Egyptian dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, what learning ſoever he hath in other matters. Againe, the vulgar charge the learn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d to have been the authors of all the hereſies which have troubled the Church; complaining that all the errors have had the originall from their ſubtilties, who have ſeduced the common people, and which cannot proceed but from learned men. But we find two ſorts of hereſies. Some more artificiall and ſubtill, which cannot proceed but from the invention of learned men, of this ranke, are thoſe who have fallen upon the attributes, and the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine decrees. The predeſtination, the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, the Union of the two Natures in Chriſt, and ſuch like points. The others more groſſe and ſtupid, as that of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thropomorphites. And theſe proceeds from imaginations of the vulgar. In generall Idolatrie hath alwaies began by ideots.</p>
               <p>Nay, the greateſt part of popery, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation of Saints, the adoration of their
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:49144:20"/>reliqnes, the worſhip of Images, the prayers for the dead have never drawne their origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, but from the ſuperſtition of the vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar. In hereſies the moſt ſubtill, the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned conduct the multitude; but in thoſe whoſe ſtuffe is more groſſe, as in the exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior practice and Ceremonies of religion, the people lead the skilfull who carried by a multitude, as by a crowd or a torrent ſuffer themſelves to be lead to the very melting of the Calfe of gold. Nay, what is more ſhamefull, one hath ſeene learned and able men moſt groſly deceived by the impoſture of idiots not only ſimple in matter of action, but moreover in things purely dogmaticall, without ſpeaking of the gravity of <hi>Tertullian</hi> miſerably ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by the dotages of <hi>Montanus,</hi> nor ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſpirits abuſed by <hi>Priſcilla,</hi> and <hi>Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milla</hi> pretended propheteſſes. The lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned who have believed ſomething of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory hath been brought to this beliefe by the revelation of ſilly devotious wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, by the apparition of ſoules, that good people ſaid they had ſeen with their eyes,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:49144:20"/>by the Enthuſiaſmes of ſome melancholy men, and by the recite of ſome Miracles, which oft-times were but effects of nature, as the nocturnall fires which often appeare in Church-yards. The errors of the firſt ſort are knowne for the moſt part by the names of ſome chiefe Hereticks, which hath produced them. Thus the blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the Sabellians, Arrians, Eutiche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Neſtorians, are marked with the name of their authors famous for having been Patriarkes of ſo many ſeverall bands of hereticks, but the errors of the ſecond ſort have not ſo certaine a Genealogie, its not ſo eaſie to name the inventors of the offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings for the dead of the adorations of Saints, or of the ſervice of Images, or the noting the time of their originall, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe theſe abuſes have bin generated from the confuſed medly of the common peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſo that the true father of them is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known. But a man may take notice of a familiar abuſe in thoſe who make uſe of humane learning; for in many religion takes ſome taint of their humours, ſo very
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:49144:21"/>often they give it the bent, or a forme ſet ſet out according to the rules of the art which they exerciſe, or of ſome other Science with which they are indued.</p>
               <p>In the greateſt part of the Fathers wee find alwaies, either in matter or phraſe ſomething which ſmells of Platoniſme, a Philoſophie which they had dranke in with their ſtudies.</p>
               <p>Afterwards that of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> came into favour, the Theologians have imitated his language, his countenance and his gate. The exceſſe to which this diſguiſe obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, was never ſo put off, but many indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to ſet it againe on foot So we have ſeen many Lawyers and Phiſitians who accommodate Theologie to the maximes of their profeſſion, not only in the tearmes, or in the method (as when the one makes it perſonall, reall and active, the others Patholotick and Therapenti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke) which is not of ſo great importance: but in the eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence it ſelf, and in the right conception of the truth thereof. So ſome meaſure the ſin of <hi>Adam,</hi> the juſtice of his puniſhment
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:49144:21"/>the quality of grace, the ſatisfaction of Chriſt, the damnation of infidells by the Lawes and rules of Civill right, or by natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall equity, having as ſleight a foundation as popular ſpirits, who conceive alwayes ſome point of their religion under maximes of their art or of the condition they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, imploying them, not as ſimple compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſons for to inlighten, but as demonſtrative proofes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 7. <hi>Why learned men receive the truth with more difficulty then other men, and if the promp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of belief is alwayes moſt praiſe worthy.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TThe ſame which we have written of the moſt piercing ſpirits happens al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to men of eminent knowledge; which is, that they are for the moſt part ſlower of belief in a point of Religion then ordinary men; &amp; there muſt be more powerfull ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, and a longer time for to draw them to the tearmes of an intire perſwaſion, on
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:49144:22"/>which I will only ſay the moſt prompt be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lief is not alwayes the moſt firm. The faith of a man who receives the Goſpell with a precipitated and eaſie approbation ought to be ſuſpected of nullity, it is to be feared its rather credulity then ſollid faith; ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly our Lord ſpake of certain auditors, who eaſily received the word with gladneſſe but left it with the ſame facility which they had brought to its reception, the truth is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes open and never hides her face to the end that he who receives her may ſee what manner of gueſt he is to receive. So when a man begins to be illuminated in the firſt acts of this faith, he meets with an infinity of objections which hinder his reſolution to an entire belief. But he which finds no obſtacles therein never conſiders thereof in good earneſt, far from having conceived the faith; a man who will ſound the depth of Religion and know the bottome as far as man can diſcover, he who will learn all the meaſures of the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle and know the dimenſions and the proportions, and weigh all the reaſons
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:49144:22"/>which forbids the entrance, and thoſe which invite him thereto; his pace will not be very faſt, and wil not come very ſoon to the altar. But if once he be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightened by the light of the Sanctuary the ſlownes thereof redounds to his advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage. for belief is far more cleare being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived <hi>upon ſolid grounds</hi> more ſound; As lodging in a ſpirit <hi>refined</hi> from all that ſurcharged it, and more ſolid as having prevented by a ripe deliberation whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver might come to ſhake it.</p>
               <p>In this tryall of religion the learned have alwayes helps which facilitates their underſtanding, and where they know to make uſe thereof they underſtand better the importance of a point of the law, or of the Goſpell, the enormity of ſinne, or the excellency of redem prion, far better then the common people. That as they have more trouble to be perſwaded, ſo they have more objections to be reſolved then thoſe which ſee not the difficulty thereof, but the perſwaſion being formed in them, poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſes all thoſe advantages which I have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated.
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:49144:23"/>And notwithſtanding it is not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether univerſally true, that the learned are the more difficult to believe the truth, the converſion of an idiot proves often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times more painfull and troubleſome. A groſſe ignorance incapable to comprehend the eaſieſt matter, is the mother of ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borneſſe; nay more, of preſumption the enemy of all knowledge: Many refuſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction becauſe they believe they have knowledge enough. So that under the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of Chriſtian liberty, an artificer cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures what he underſtands not.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 8. <hi>Why the learned are ſubject to more doubts then the ſimple people.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WE find an infinite number of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons among the common people, who never doubt of any point of faith, nor of any other matter approved by the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodoxall Church, whereas that ordinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the moſt knowing men are full of doubts. Now its true, that believing and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:49144:23"/>doubting are acts formally contrary: for diſtruſt (although many teach it) is not of the eſſence of faith, no more then vice is not eſſentiall to vertue, and every ſort of doubt is a teſtimony of our weakneſſe, and a mark of ignorance. But it is eaſie to judge from whence it comes that popular ſpirits are not ſubject to ſo many doubts as the great Theologians: For as thier ſight extends not it ſelf ſo farre, ſo they ſee not all the difficulties which the other diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver in the ſtudy of Religion; as for thoſe who have never doubted of any point, it is of neceſſity that this great ſecurity of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit proceeds from one of thoſe two cauſes either of a perfect and tranſcendent faith, incompatible with all ſpecies of doubt, or from an extreame ſtupidity, which never comprehended the importance of a do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, nor ever ſounded the depth thereof. A man who hath alwayes had an abſolute and unvariable perſwaſion of all points of Religion without any contradicting thought, muſt neceſſarily be either An an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſ or a beaſt. This ſtupid, confidence de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:49144:24"/>an infinity of ſouls, eſpecially in the perſonall application of their beliefe. Many hold themſelves ſo aſſured of their ſalvation, that their ſpirit is incapable of doubting; but not through the excellency of faith, which requires a more exact triall but through an exceſse of ſelf love; from hence it comes to paſse they willingly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve whatſoever makes for their advantage. But if they have no pertinent reaſons, it is a moſt groſse preſumption.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 9 <hi>Of common proverbs in generall and of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain maximes in favour of ignorance.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE vulgar people governe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by certain maximes eſteemed for oracles, but which are indeed as many approved errours.</p>
               <p>The proverbs which belong to Oecono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, exteriour policie, and to naturall prudence in the conduct of our lives, are nothing to our purpoſe, there are ſome which touch Religion, that are held for
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:49144:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>aſsured principalls which have nothing but an abuſive and fraudulent appearance; whoſoever would make the inventory ſhould diſcover a thouſand abſurdities. For all the proverbiall ſentences which are at this day in uſe, have not been dictated by the mouth of the wiſe or from reaſon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to all men or from univerſall experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
               <p>Ignorance hath brought forth many which are authoriſed onely by the credit of the multitude. And every man who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires to underſtand very well his Religion, ought to take of theſe prejudicated pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbs, which at this time have courſe, ſuch are the following maximes, to wit, <hi>That there's no ſin but with the will,</hi> which is falſe. Originall ſinne in little children, omiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons proceeding from forgetfulneſse, the firſt motions which are not in the power of man, extravagant dreames, wandering and idle thoughts, doubtles, which trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the ſpirit, are not voluntary, and not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding are ſtill ſinnes. Idiots ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that ſinne reſides not but in the will,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:49144:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>not conſidering that it hath its place in the Intellect it ſelf, but this is to juſtifie that opinion which ſome hold that <hi>Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance is no ſinne, but when it is voluntary.</hi> But the Law, the rule of our conceptions, obligeth ignorance namely that which is not voluntary to come under the expiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and purgation of ſacrifices: which preſuppoſeth a fault, Jeſus Chriſt died as well for our ignorance as for our other ſinnes. The holy language when it ſpeaks of a ſinner uſeth a terme, which fignifieth an ignorant, the high prieſt prayed for the ignorants, that is he prayed for the ſinners. The eye to wit, the underſtanding; is called evill although its malignity conſiſts in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but in errour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That it is better to have piety then know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> But knowledge is the beſt part of piety: the new man is renewed in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: whatſoever any man may ſay, an ignorant man can never be a good Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, all his vertues are none. Nay more, there is nothing ſo dangerous as an ignorant Zelot.</p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:49144:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>That we have knowledge enough, and that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting but the practice,</hi> but if any one believe he knows enough, as yet he knows nothing, ſeeing that he is ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of his own ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: if any one ſhould ask that man which is ſo perfect in the knowledge of his Religion, from whence it proceeds that they fail ſo much in their practice; they alleadge the corruption of their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture preſuppoſing that it lodgeth onely in the affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s or in the wil, as if the intellect were altogether exempt: Nevertheleſſe if the eye of the ſoule, which is the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, if this eye were pure, all its actions would be full of light. It is true that the greateſt part of thoſe that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit evill know that it is unlawfull, but they believe to find their good therein which is a capital errour. A man who kills himſelf believes that death is better to him then life; the higheſt mover to ſinne will be alwayes found in, the falſeneſſe of the judgement, and in the unjuſt perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the ſpirit, or becauſe we do not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand God rightly, but onely curſorily
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:49144:26"/>under ſome generall notions, without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending to the ſpecies &amp; circumſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces; or we underſtand without believing it. Or we believe it but with ſo weak a faith, that it is eaſily turned aſide; It is true that we have knowledge enough, to make us inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſable, but never too much to make us better.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That works of Charity are the moſt viſible marks of a Chriſtian.</hi> This maxime is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to experience; we cannot diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern a Chriſtian from a Jew by alms or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of benificency, which the one may exerciſe as well as the other, the firſt mark which makes a Chriſtian to be known is the confeſſion of his faith, there is not a ſect how deſperate ſoever, but can furniſh ſome examples of probity, temperance and of all vertues, whatſoever. Many hereticks, have cover'd the foulnes of their errours by the ſplend our of their charitable life, if we muſt among ſo many congregations diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in doctrine diſpute which is the moſt innocent in reſpect of manners, the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſt would carry away the priſe. We ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:49144:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>yet granted to the <hi>Romane</hi> Catholicks that holineſſe of life was a mark of the true Church, and we do affirm that the impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of their manners had been no lawfull cauſe of our ſeparation. <hi>That a Chriſtian is not obliged to learn any thing, but in as much as it conduces to his ſalvation.</hi> This bold aſſertion carries not the mark of final obedience. Many believe themſelves to be very pious, becauſe they have a great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be happy, and the reaſon why they hearken to the Scripture is becauſe it may make them happy. Now it is moſt true that God hath made his word the conduit pipe of our ſalvation, but we ought not onely for this reſpect to hearken to it, but in as much as it is the word of God to which we owe our attention although it were againſt our owne profit. Thoſe whoſe practice is otherwiſe, are more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous of their own ſalvation then of their Saviour, and that their devotion proves but mercenary; But this maxime ſerves as a pretext to another errour; None dares abſolutely ſay that the Scripture
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:49144:27"/>contains any thing but that it ſerves to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. Nevertheleſſe beſides an infinite number of hiſtories, all the genealogies, chronologies, etimologies of proper names deſcription of countries, and of buildings; ceremoniall ordinances, propheticall em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blemes, the inwreathing of myſteries, and divers other pieces of Scripture are ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous in the judgement of the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty, becauſe they ſee not to what uſe it ſerves towards their ſalvation; He that would raſe out all that ignorant men hold to be unprofitable muſt reduce the Bible to the fourth part of what it containes, where as the Romiſh Church believes they ought to adde thereto.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That a Chriſtian ought to content him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with that which is ſimply neceſsary to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,</hi> which is as much to ſay that a man ought to know no more of Religion but juſt as much as will ſerve him to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, as if it were a dangerous thing to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand too well his ſalvation, for to have too many Torches to conduct him to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven under colour that a little ſpark or a
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:49144:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſmoaking ſnuffe may give him ſufficient light, I believe for certain that God hath had mercy upon many Idiots, who never knew of what tribe our Lord deſcended according to the fleſh, nor of what fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly was the virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> nor whether <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> preceded <hi>Moſes.</hi> But this ignorance is not pardoned to all. A certain meaſure of knowledge will be ſufficient to ſave one, which will not ſuffice for the ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of another; More belongs to a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor in Theologie then to a lay man; to him that ſits in the chaire of the Prophets, then him that ſits at their footſtool, to a man that hath lived forty years in the Church, then to an American or another proſelyte who never heard ſpeak of Jeſus Chriſt, but at the houre of his death.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That a Chriſtian hath not need of much knowledge for to be ſaved.</hi> It is a favourable prejudication to thoſe who are negligent but moſt dangerous in matters of ſuch conſequence; If man knew how difficult it were to be ſaved he would never thinke the gate of heaven ſo large that the blinde
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:49144:28"/>might paſſe through without knowing of it, if there be any thing in which agility, dexterity, skill, knowledge are requiſite it is in this point. It belongs to none but thoſe which are wiſe to obtain the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heaven.</p>
               <p>It is true the goodneſſe of God ſaves an infinity of ſimple Idiots inlightned onely with ſome glimmering of his knowledge, but it is moſt ſure that many of them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it in a greater meaſure in the laſt moment of their lives; for this light may come at once, as a lightning which paſſes from the Eaſt to the Weſt, and diſcovers in a wink both the length, and the large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and the depth of many doctrines which he could never have ſo well compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended, though he ſhould have ſtudied 30 years. One only night at the foot of <hi>Jacobs</hi> ladder will make him ſee more miſeries then a multitude of clear and bright ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning dayes in a well furniſhed library. The thief learnt more Theology hanging by Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus in a quarter of an houre then many great Doctours have gotten all their life. I
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:49144:28"/>ſtop not at thoſe ſpeculations which they alledge upon this queſtion from whence it proceeds, that ſometimes one hath ſeene ignorants being on their bed of death with deliberate judgement diſcourſe of the higheſt points of faith with as much depth and in as good tearmes as the moſt accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſht Theologians; Whether it be that the ſoul being as it were half looſed from the body, begins as then to ſoare aloft, and to diſcover that it never ſaw before, or that it being illuminated with a greater light, it perceives what it had never before learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; I leave the deciſion thereof. But this grace is not common, nor doth it autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe a voluntary ignorance nor the practice of the common people, whoſe knowledge is at this day reduced to the onely rudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of faith. Nor the carelesneſſe, nor the inſufficiency of many preachers who never give any thing but milk to their au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors under pretext that it is the word of God, for to keep them in perpetuall infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ey and far from perfection.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="section">
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:49144:29"/>
            <head>The ſecond Section.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER 1. <hi>Divinity reduced into a verball ſcience a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of tearmes, as well ſcholaſtick as Oratorian: A difference in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect amongſt the Sciences: an objection touching the ſtile of the Scripture.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N theſe times a man is held for learned, although he knows many words, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in effect he knows very little of the ſubſtance; the knowledge of many which are reputed for learned, conſiſts rather in tearmes then in reality; A collection of words heaped up in the braine to the bigneſſe of a moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, contains oft times but an atome, the production whereof is ridiculous: they are ſo multiplied, by a labour full of vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that there is more time ſpent in lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:49144:29"/>the tearms then the thing it ſelf, and in the end of our ſtudies its found: we know a quantity of words, but ſcarce: any ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiall matters, if one ſhould gather all the tearms which are naturaliſed in The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ologie and the divers ſences of each one of them; he would make a dictionary whoſe volume would ſurpaſſe foure Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles. If there be any thing in which our knowledge is ſtraightened in narrow bounds it is the myſtery of the Trinity, all which men can ſay inſubſtance is redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced into very few words. Nevertheleſſe beſides the tearms of Eſſentiall, Perſonall, Conſubſtantiall and others whoſe intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction hath been made neceſſary by the importunity of hereſies we heare ſpoken of, Active and Paſſive Generation, like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe of Active and Paſſive Spiration, and Proceſſion of emperichoriſie of abſolute properties, and relative properties, of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geneſia, or ingenerability of works, exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, and of works internall, of divided and undivided operations of reall and modall diſtinctions, of a diſtinction Characteriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:49144:30"/>of the ſuppoſed ſuppoſitive and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſmes, ſuppoſitions, The principles attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes ſubſtantiall &amp; Oeconomicall attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes, the Endiathetick, &amp; the word Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoric, reflexively, a production by the way of the intellect, and by the way of the will, a production Phyſicall and Metaphyſicall, &amp; Hyperphyſicall, Notionall acts; the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract &amp; the Concret. The Miſſion taken Actively, and the Miſſion taken Paſſively; the communication of Idiomes, and an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finity of other words many of which are not altogether unprofitable, but the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of them ſhews our knowledge to be more verball then Reall. One of the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt points of our knowledge conſiſts in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctions; Now it is moſt certain, that there is more diſtinction of termes, then of things themſelves, the onely word of faith is taken in ſo many differing ſignifications that it requires a great deal of ſtudy. This knowledge is neceſſary to a Theologian, but conſidering it in it ſelf, it gives at no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther quality but the knowledge of diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing of ſyllables, like thoſe who know
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:49144:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>all the differences, names of a plant, and yet are ignorant of the vertues thereof. In the mean while we ſee ſome who will diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>play a conception as a rare and miſterious doctrine which in the depth contains no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther skill, but the clearing of an ambiguous word, the ſurpluſage being nothing, but ſome triviall matter.</p>
               <p>Now beſides the multitude of termes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready received, and as yet remain, in caſe they each day invent new ones, ſo that the language of <hi>Canaan</hi> hath the leaſt part in Religion: and if Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſhould again return into the world ſcarce would he be capable to be received Doctor in Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy for want of having ſtudied <hi>Thomas A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinas,</hi> for the points of Religion have o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther names then thoſe by which they were called in his time, and for one name that they then had there, they give them a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred at this day, beſides thoſe which they have given to new matters, which all the Apoſtles never knew.</p>
               <p>The Common people think that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge conſiſts in the abundance of words,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:49144:31"/>although that twenty different words ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie but the ſame thing, an ignorant fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low thinks he knows much becauſe he knows many ſynonimies; This error ought to be attribured either to the ignorance or to the negligence of many Preachers and compoſers of books, fertill in words, bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren in ſubſtance, whoſe inſtructions are more verball then doctrinall. The art to amplifie a diſcourſe, through a diverſity of words and phraſes equivolent in ſence and gilded over ſometimes with interrogations ſometimes with Allegories, ſometimes with Apoſtrophes, with Proſopoeia's; theſe circumlocutions would not be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent if they alwayes brought along with them ſome new reality, which ſhould not onely augment the diſcourſe, but alſo the Subject and matter thereof, otherwiſe to produce one onely conception ſtretched out in words as if it were new matter un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der colour that they repreſent it in divers <hi>veſtes</hi> and different poſtures, it is a cunning more fit for a ſtage then a Pulpit.</p>
               <p>Theſe Retoricall amplifications are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:49144:31"/>into ſome certain ſciences, in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers they are altogether unprofitable. Phyſick hath nothing to do therewith, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in reſpect of the Theory, nor of the practice. The Mathematicks ſuffer it not; it would be ridiculous to demonſtrate the proportion of the diameter, to the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, or the Roots of the numbers, in Panegyricks, and Rethoricall declamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; The Theologian and the Lawyer one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly employ them, the reaſons is that the end of theſe two profeſſions is not onely to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct and to inform the judgement of the auditors, but alſo to move their affections to what elſe ſerves the ornament, and the copiouſneſſe of a language; but Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy is not onely to move the affections (as ignorant men ſuppoſe) The firſt vertue of a Chriſtian conſiſts in the knowledge of God and of his works. Knowledge which cannot be but onely in the intellect which is inſtructed by proofs, and reall and direct demonſtrations not by the windings and turnings of words, or exaggerating of things, which oftener clouds the truth,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:49144:32"/>more then it enlighteneth, it enlightens it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
               <p>But one may object that the Scripture it ſelf is not every where logicall in all it parts, for it not onely teaches by axiome or univerſall rules, by conciſe diſtinction or ſimple Propoſitions, but alſo by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes and threatnings, by examples extend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the length by ordinary ſimilitude by diverſity of paraphraſes and frequen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> repetitions: to which we anſwer the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ought to be explained, and not to be made more intricate, that the amplifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, metaphors and compariſons in which the Scripture extends it ſelf, nay the very repetitions, and that which is moſt verball in it, are full of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities of which we ſhall give ſome exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:49144:32"/>
               <head>CHAP. 2. <hi>The matters of the Scripture made verball by the ignorant, the ſolidity of its ſtile, myſteries turned into Retoricall figures.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TO ſay the ſame thing in divers tearmes, and in a multitude of words is a repetition which may ſerve to refreſh the memory, or to move the affections, but brings no new thing to the intellect. The ignorant deceive them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, if they believe that the repetitions which are in the Scripture are of no other quality but Grammaticall or Retoricall; when the Scripture repeats any point, this repetition declares ſomething elſe more then it had ſaid the firſt time. In one and the ſame paſſage the repetition of the ſame word is not alwayes a <hi>Pleonaſme,</hi> for to give an <hi>Emphaſis</hi> to the diſcourſe, or to inculcate that which had already been ſpoken, to the end that it ſhould be the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter remembred. The repetitions of the Scripture alwayes bring ſome addition, and termes which ſeem Synonimies have
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:49144:33"/>ſometimes different ſignifications. The twelve Patriarks are called to the Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their father in theſe termes, <hi>Come together ye children of</hi> Jacob, <hi>hearken to Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el your father.</hi> Theſe words contain in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance a ſuperfluous tautologie. For it ſeemes it was enough to have called them children of <hi>Jacob</hi> without adding that <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> was their father, ſeeing that <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> was one and the ſame perſon. But as one of theſe two names was a majeſtick title that God had conferred upon his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and the other was rather a mark of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach. The Patriarks are called children of <hi>Jacob</hi> to the end they ſhould remember their low extraction, and to take notice that their father ſpak to them in quality of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> A Prince with God, whoſe words were nothing but oracles. Theſe two names having been tranſmitted to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire body of his poſterity are very often joyned together for to denoate on, and the ſame people. <hi>They ſhall teach</hi> (ſaid <hi>Moſes) thy judgements to</hi> Jacob <hi>and thy law to Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell,</hi> that is they ſhall teach the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:49144:33"/>weak in faith, comprehended under the name of <hi>Jacob</hi> and the moſt eminent repreſented under the title of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in the ſame ſort as Chriſt recommended unto <hi>Peter, the feeding not onely of his lambs, but alſo of his ſheep.</hi> The vulgar people know no difference between <hi>Lawes, Ordinances, and Judgements, betwixt Commandements and Statutes,</hi> tearmes which are oft times joyned in one and the ſame paſſage, but are very different in their ſignification which the ignorant ordinarily confound; the two dreames of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> were but one and the ſame, and it ſeems as if the ſecond were ſuperflous, ſeeing that it ſaid nothing in ſubſtance which had not been ſpoken in the firſt. But beſides the diverſity of fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures produced in theſe two dreams which teacheth diverſity of circumſtances under this differency of ſhapes, he who was the interpreter marks this repetition, as devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſomething more, then as if the dream had come but once. It imports much to know how often one thing hath been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated in the ſame place of the Scripture
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:49144:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>without diſputing if theſe words of <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remy, Say not the temple of the Lord, the temple of the Lord, the temple of the Lord</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſed the Jewes not to hope for a third temple. It is certain that the number of reiterations is oft entimes miſterious. If S. <hi>Peter</hi> had remembred that he had denied his Maſter, thrice he would have wondred why our Lord ſaid unto him thrice <hi>loveſt thou me.</hi> In <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 28. God ſaid to the King of <hi>Tire. All the precious ſtones covered thee, The Carbuncle, the Topaz, the Diamond the Berill, the Sardonix, the Jaſper, the Sap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phir, the Chriſolite, and the Emeraud thou walkeſt amongſt the precious ſtones:</hi> Many do not ſee in this diſcourſe any thing but a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoricall deſcription, enlarged by the am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plification of magnificent words, w<hi rend="sup">he</hi> one word ſeemingly means nothing elſe but that this Prince was rich, and opulent. But whoſoever will remember that all theſe precious ſtones had place in the breaſtplate of the High Prieſt, that each one of them carried the name of a Tribe, that one of the Predeceſſors of this King of <hi>Tire</hi> had
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:49144:34"/>had part in the glory of theſe Tribes, by the honour that God did him to accept his materialls, and his workmen for the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick of the Temple. Whoſoever ſay, I will fixedly regard theſe precious ſtones, will find that they contain farre greater lights then the Luſtre of a verball ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, and ſome reaſon may be given, why that two or three, of theſe tribes are omitted in this deſcription of <hi>Ezechiel.</hi> If this ſence be obſcure in this paſſage cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly it is evident in the foundations of the celeſtiall <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> painted out in the 21 of the <hi>Apocalips,</hi> which being repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented in divers ſorts of precious ſtones, differing in their ſpecies diſtinguiſhed by their names, placed each one in his proper rank and reduced to a certain number which neither ſuffers Addition, nor ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction cannot be taken onely for a heap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing together of words of amplification, the alluſion of them to the twelve ſtones in the pectorall is altogether manifeſt, and the ranging of them altogether different from the order which <hi>Moſes</hi> gave them
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:49144:35"/>produces a myſticall reflection of many high myſteries, both in the one, and the other Teſtament; we might make an infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite of paſſages to this purpoſe. But al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in many of them we find not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes the true ſubſtance of the fruit the Scripture hides under this abundance of flowers, it is there notwithſtanding and teſtifies the ſottiſh vanity of ſo many commentators which think they have di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to the bottome of the Ark; when af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a curious ſearch they find there an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaſis of the <hi>Grammar</hi> or an <hi>Epiſtrophe,</hi> as if a figure of Rethorick were a myſtery of Theologie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:49144:35"/>
               <head>CHAP. 3. <hi>The eſſence of Christianity annihilated by the maximes of the vulgar, who reduce Religion into morality, which is the moſt excellent and moſt neceſsary doctrine of Religion. A difference between the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod of Philoſophers and the order that Theologie ſets forth in the inſtruction of manners.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE common people holds that all Religion conſiſts in practice or in works; that all Chriſtianity lies in the doctrine of good works, or at leaſt that this doctrine of good manners is the principal part and the foundation of Religion. Theſe maximes are very pleaſing, whereupon they repreſent faith, the tongues know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, propheſie, as unprofitable qualities without Charity. The greateſt idiots are greateſt Orators in this point and ſet forth excellently the praiſe of good works which indeed cannot be too much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended: But yet it is a greater error then
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:49144:36"/>think of, to imagine Religion to be one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a doctrine of manners, whereupon we muſt mark theſe following poſitions.</p>
               <p n="1">1 The doctrine of Religion hath two parts, the firſt ſhews what God hath done for man, the other teacheth what man ought to do for God, the firſt compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends, after the conſideration of the eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God and of his perfections the intire Oeconomy of his works in nature, in grace, and in glory. The ſecond deline<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates all Chriſtian vertues, as well intelle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall as Morall.</p>
               <p n="2">2 This firſt part is the true and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall Character which diſtinguiſheth chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians from all others: For there is no falſe Religion whatſoever, but teacheth many excellent morallities; but to teach what God hath done for us eſpecially in the work of our redemption is a doctrine which is not to be found, but in the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion.</p>
               <p n="3">3 The true eſſence of Chriſtianity, ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in this part, for all other Religions teach ſalvation by the work of man to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:49144:36"/>God but ours teacheth this ſalvation as a work of God towards man.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Ignorant men think that Religion is nothing but a Law, and ſo confound the difference between the Law and the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell and ſo annihilate Chriſtianity it ſelf.</p>
               <p n="5">5 The greateſt corruption which ever came into the Church began by thoſe maximes, which commended morall do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, as being the whole ſubſtance of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, for ſo it came to paſſe, that finally Chriſtianity was reduced into morality; if one will mark the conſequences of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny opinions newly introduced, he will find they all ſhoot at this mark.</p>
               <p n="6">6 Its an impiety to affirm that the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of works is the foundation of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, or at leaſt it is ſpoken very inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately. For ſalvation which is the true ſubject of Religion, is grounded upon that good which God doth to us, not upon the good which we do, from whence this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult doth proceed, that the fundamentall doctrine of Chriſtianity is not that which teacheth us good manners, but to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:49144:37"/>that part which we call morrall hath his foundation upon the firſt.</p>
               <p n="7">7 Then it is but a raſh aſſertion to maintain that that doctrine which ſpeaks of manners, is the moſt excellent part of Religion. For if the nobleneſſe of a ſcience depends upon the excellency of a ſubject without diſpute that part which concerns God and his works, is more ſublime and elevated then that which handles the works of man; nay more this ſecond part cannot have any place, but as a conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of the other; all Chriſtian vertues are effects of ſanctification which is a work of God.</p>
               <p n="8">8 But they do alledge that Morall doctrine is moſt neceſſary, and that they ought more to inſiſt upon that, then upon the firſt. To which we anſwer, that the firſt part is that which gives the eſſence to the other, and is the ſource and <hi>primum mobile</hi> to all vertue. 'Tis it which furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us with lights, without which all our morality would be dark and heatheniſh. And though this ſhould not be, it would
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:49144:37"/>be a great error to believe that it were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for a good Chriſtian to be a good moraliſt; to the inſtruction of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans Religion hold a contrary method to that which is uſed in Philoſophy; for it is all one to Philoſophers, whether they teach the practicall ſciences before the contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plative, foraſmuch as that morality or pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticks do not borrow their principalls from Mathematicks, or Phiſick. But in Religion, Theologick vertues which rule all others, cannot be extended without a foreknowledge of their object. Now this object which is God himſelf is not known but by his works, ſo that a Chriſtian ought to know what God hath done for him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he can underſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d what he ought to do for God. The Law it ſelf in the frontiſpice of the Decalogue before that it ſpeaks of our duty towards God teacheth us what he is, and what he hath done for us. Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally it is to be conſider'd that the moſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary part of religion is that which han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles the cauſes of our ſalvatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as is the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on &amp; office of Chriſt our juſtification, &amp;
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:49144:38"/>Now theſe points are not morrall do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>Why common people loves not rather to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in manners, then in any other point of religion. Everyone hath a naturall o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion to be ſaved by his workes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis part of Religion which we call morall, is more pleaſing to the common people, and a better eare given thereto then the other. The reaſon is, becauſe the generall rules of good man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and the principalls of vertue, are na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally known to the moſt blockiſh. From thence it comes to paſſe, that this kind of doctrine pleaſeth them, as being in part na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall, and becauſe of its facility; For an Idcot hath no great paine to comprehend that he ought to render to each one what belongs unto him; and that one ought to have compaſſion of the afflicted, and other precepts which nature makes intelligible.
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:49144:38"/>But the other matters becauſe they are for the moſt part ſupernaturall and miſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, find not ſo favourable an attention in the Auditors; Behold yet more which we have to marke; which is a naturall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicate opinion in man, when one ſpeaks of the obtaining of ſalvation, they thinke incontinently on works, as the true cauſe which ought produce that effect; The Jews taking it for granted, askes not our Lord, but upon the quality of workes, <hi>John</hi> 6.28. All the men of the world except Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans build upon their workes, they not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to imagine any other merrit for to be ſaved.</p>
               <p>Now this principall is naturall, as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been ingraffed in the heart of man e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſince his creation, to wit, that he ſhould have eternall life by his workes; Which was true in the eſtate of innocencie, for Workes would have produced this effect if man had not loſt his forces. Now hee leaves as yet on this principall, the impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion whereof he hath retained, although that his fall having broken all his bones,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:49144:39"/>ſhewes him that his pretenſions are but vaine. From this fountaine proceeds not only the opinions which attribute the effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy of ſalvation to workes, but alſo the maximes of the common people, who ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging the impuiſſance of workes in this regard; nevertheleſſe ſo highly elevates the dignity of them, that hee thinkes that the preaching modeſty in cloathes is a more excellent doctrine, then to teach them all the miſteries of the Goſpell.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>The Scripture made abſurd by vulgar, and by thoſe Preachers who turne it into mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality. Popular vertues.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WHat the common people ſeekes principally in the Scripture is ſome morrall inſtruction, certainly neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary beyond what is ſpoken. But many beleeving that the Scripture ought not to containe any other thing, reduce it all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to morality, namely the Hiſtories in which
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:49144:39"/>they conſider no other ſubject, but the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples either of vice, or of vertue. This ignorance which turnes the moſt elevated miſteries into ſimple morall precepts in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduceth a thouſand abſurdities in the Scripture, in which we meet with divers narrations, which if taken only morrally, would be found very impertinent. The bargaine made between <hi>Lea</hi> and <hi>Rachel, Gen.</hi> 30.14. the contention betweene <hi>Sara</hi> and <hi>Hagar,</hi> the childiſh ſtrife betwixt <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Iſmael,</hi> if we bring no other concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions then thoſe of the vulgar, theſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters would be both frivolous and ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous; certainly, theſe hiſtories carry a dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſence. And S. <hi>Paul, Gal.</hi> 4.24.) finding in theſe two laſt the Image of the moſt important truths which are in religion which ſhewes that the intention of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt was cleare otherwiſe then only to paint forth ſimple moralities.</p>
               <p>More faulty is as yet the ſtile of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite number of Preachers, who believe they handle the Scripture very well, ſo that they diſguiſe all in Tropes. If they
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:49144:40"/>handle the miraculous healing of the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prous, all their diſcourſe will be of the ſpirituall Leproſie; If of the reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of one dead, they will ſpeake only of regeneration; turning theſe hiſtories out of their naturall ſence, and omitting in the meane time the conſiderations which they furniſh us to the true underſtanding of the place; Truly, its permitted to draw an inſtruction for manners from an article of the faith; but it is a great folly to lay hold of the concommitant of a ſubject, in ſtead of the principall, and make the body of their diſcourſe thereof. When any will expreſly handle a morall doctrine the Scripture abounds in formall paſſages for ſuch matters, otherwiſe hee ſhould both mock them, and his auditors to preach the decalogue in interpreting the Symbole. But it is eaſier for the ignorant to preach morality, then to handle a point more mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterious, only for to bring it forth after their ordinary faſhion in groſſe equipage, and under triviall reaſons; For to handle worthily a doctrine of manners one ought
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:49144:40"/>to have proviſion of rare matters and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions, elevated above the common, which belongs not but to a profound The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ologian. The vulgar knowes the vertues by their habits, then in their eſſence. Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular piety abounds ſo in certaine acts that it neglects the others, namely, all charity at this day is reduced into almes; Many love rather to nouriſh a poore man, then to convert an Idolater, although it be a greater worke of charity to ſave one ſoule, then to feed a hundred thouſand bellies. Otherwiſe a man who had founded Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talls, ſhould have done a farre more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent worke then all the labours of the Apoſtles.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:49144:41"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Touching curioſities, Raſh queſtions of thoſe which are returned from the dead: Of the Divell who exhorted to repentance: Of the knowledge of evill.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MAn never ſaw the creation of any thing: when God would forme <hi>Eve,</hi> he made <hi>Adam</hi> ſleep; So likewiſe he hath reſerved to himſelfe the judgement of three points; 1. of his councells; 2. of Scripture, 3. of conſciences. To inquire of the Son, proceeds of the Father, as of the Intellect, and the holy Ghoſt as of the will. What had been the poſterity of <hi>Adam,</hi> if he had not falne, and if in this caſe the Sonne of God would have cloathed himſelfe with our fleſh; or if the ſacred body of Jeſus Chriſt was perfectly organified from the firſt moment of his conception, if God could not have ſaved man by any other meanes, then by the death of his Sonne. And whether Jeſus Chriſt by his ſufferan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces hath merited his proper exaltation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:49144:41"/>our ſalvation; are moſt raſh curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities.</p>
               <p>If any one ſhould riſe againe from the dead, our curioſity would aske him a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand queſtions, but I marke that of all thoſe who ever riſe againe, not one (except our Lord) is introduced, ſpeaking in the Scripture, except we put into this ranke, <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> in the transfiguration, which nevertheleſſe ſpake not but of the death of Jeſus Chriſt. Though a man ſhould come from heaven, hee could not name the things which he had ſeene or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, becauſe that it never having mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into the thought of man, they could not impoſe names thereto. So that thoſe things could not be declared but in tearms, the ſence whereof would be unknown unto us, they are words uneffable, which man cannot pronounce, and ought not to affect. If the dead ought to be our inſtructors, the ſpirit of error would eaſily counterfeit them, and under this pretext would autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe his impoſtures. The Scripture of all the damned names, but only <hi>Judas,</hi> and
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:49144:42"/>would not expreſſe the name, the evill rich. But many ſpirits which they pretend to be returned from the other world particula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe by names and ſurnames the ſoules they have ſeen in hell. For the vulgar preſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that they know one another, and that the Devill knows all that are within his bottomles pit. Upon this imagination the Exorciſts believing they have the power to make him tell nothing but truth, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of curious things, taking pleaſure to make him talk; whereas Jeſus Chriſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver made him ſpeak but once, impoſing ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence upon them in all other deliverance of thoſe, out of whom he had caſt the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils. Namely, it is not long ſince the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil preached repentance by the mouth of ſome, which were poſſeſſed, his words have been gathered and publiſhed in a groſſe volume by men bearing the title of approved theologians which have alledged them for a very perſwaſive argument of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment of life, ſhowing that the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil who took upon him this office was ſent by God to convert men, ſeeing that
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:49144:42"/>the other wayes were unprofitable, farre from repulſing the impudency of this adverſary, who ſpeaks not of piety but by mockery, or for to render it ſuſpected be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of which when he would have ſpoken in favour of the truth, our Lord made him alwayes hold his peace.</p>
               <p>All unlawfull curioſities have relation unto two heads, whoſe inquiſition is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden us, to wit the hight of heaven and the depth of hell.</p>
               <p>The Scripture praiſeth thoſe who have not known the depths of Satan. A too ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act knowledge of evill offends the ſpirit, and a man well skilled in malice although that it but in Theory will ever now and then give a taſt thereof; The diligence of Caſuiſts to examine all the ſpecies of ſins namely thoſe whoſe onely name ſtrikes a horror to our eares hath been a perniious labour, more capable to deſtroy good man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, then to inſtruct the conſciences.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:49144:43"/>
               <head>CHAP. 7. <hi>Wherefore Scholaſtick Theologie was invented and how it was establiſhed: with a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary ſucceſse.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THree things have made Scholaſticall Theology to be cried down, ſetting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide the impurity, <hi>des dogmes</hi> of their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, with which it is ſtuffed.</p>
               <p n="1">1 The multitude of Philoſophicall mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. 2 The vain curioſitie of queſtions. 3 the barbarouſneſſe of the language; the intention of thoſe who built it was to keep the key of knowledge among themſelves, and to hinder the common people from entering therein, and to take from them the knowledge of Theologie, to this effect they ſtopt the gap with thorns, and made the paſſage difficult. Firſt mingling Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy therewith, nay all the moſt ſubtil ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culations of Metaphyſicks, then reducing the whole Chriſtian doctrine into high and tickliſh queſtions, which the vulgar neither durſt nor could approach, and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:49144:43"/>inventing a certain canting of ſtrange and unexplicable words as the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians having their tearmes and Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters not to be underſtood, but onely by thoſe of the ſame profeſſion.</p>
               <p>Now this Theologie begins to be intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced amongſt us, the principall matters which they handle at this time, are the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine decrees, with all their conſequences. There be thoſe which find the depth of the higheſt ſecrets of God; nothing is unknown unto them neither in heaven nor hell, and their mouths bring forth words uneffable which themſelves underſtand not: For theſe new ſtuffes ſtill have new names, and it is to be feared in the end leaſt all the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Religion ſhould again turn Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtick. But this Metamorphoſis hath not the ſame ſucceſſe which it had in times paſt for the ancient Scolaſtick theology be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing invented for to keep the people in a ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid ſilence held it ſelf in the compaſſe of the cloyſters, and of the univerſities; but the Modern have leapt into the Pulpit of the Churches, from thence to the market
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:49144:44"/>places, to the ſhops to the tables, and into the brains of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon people, to fill them with ſcruples, cries, and contentious diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes, and to make them fight for a ſubject which for the moſt part they underſtand not.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 8. <hi>The boldneſse of the vulgar, the laſt Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans ought to know more then the firſt. The modern Church ought to be called ancient.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THAT which we have ſpoken ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifies not the temerity of ignorant men, who preſently condemne all matters or queſtions which ſurpaſſe their capacity. The vulgar are wonderfully bold to reject as curious each doctrine which they underſtand not or they judge it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable, under colour that they do not comprehend the importance thereof, or they accuſe it of novelty, becauſe they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver heard of it: before we give examples thereof we ſhall produce ſome obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:49144:44"/>Our age is reputed worſe then the precedent. If this complaint be as true as it is common, let thoſe judge who will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the ancient and the modern occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences. Certainly in one point our age ſurpaſſeth others, and in the ſame reſpect poſterity will ſurpaſſe our ſelves, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the knowledge of many things un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to the ages paſt, a knowledge which facilitates the Scriptures in divers matters which our forefathers fifteen ages paſt could never find the intelligence of ſetting aſide the diſcovery of the new world, and a thouſand other wonders which have hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened ſince them, many Propheſiess have been dark unto them, which at this day are as cleare as the ſun: for their accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hath diſſipated the obſcurity and knowledge hath multiplied from time to time according to the meaſure that the lamb hath opened the ſeales of his oracles.</p>
               <p>The name of antiquiry hath abuſed ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, the Church which was then and which is at this day are but one univerſall Church in reſpect of time, the difference of ages
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:49144:45"/>makes us to diſtinguiſh into two, calling it the ancient and the new, but by tranſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of names, for we call it ancient, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering it in the firſt ages, in which it was yong &amp; new, &amp; to the contrary, we qualifie it new, in this time in which it ought to be called ancient, as having obtain'd to a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter age; notwithſtanding taking Antiquity in the ordinary ſence, it may teach vs very much, principally for hiſtorie, and mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters which conſiſt in action. But as by this meanes we may know that which our forefathers have known, we have moreover this advantage, that we know many things which were unknown to them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:49144:45"/>
               <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>Concerning that Maxime; That we cannot ſay any thing but what hath been already ſpoken.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis popular opinion ſerves for a pretext of ignorance, and of care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſſe to many men. They would be much troubled if one ſhould aske them if this maxime had been alwayes true e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſince the beginning of the world, for then it would follow, that whatſoever came ſince the firſt man ſhould have beene ſpoken before, and ſo of neceſſitie that <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> had ſpoken of <hi>David,</hi> of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Solomon,</hi> of <hi>Pilate,</hi> and of the Romans of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the great, and of <hi>Charlemaine.</hi> If this axiome hath not been alwaies true in what time began it then to be; when all things hath been made an end to be ſpoken who made up the cloſure; but certainly the aſſertion hath not been alwaies true, not in Philoſophie to whom nature and experience have diſcovered from time to
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:49144:46"/>time many things unknowne to antiquity. Not in Phyſick, which hath ſeen new di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes produced, and hath found out new remedies; Not in the Politicall ſcience to whom occurrences have ſuggeſted lawes unthought of by the Ancients. Not in Mathematicks, which have produced new inventions unknown to our Fathers. Not in Hiſtory which each day is inlarged, and will never faile to find new ſubjects. Not in Mechannick arts, many of which have been invented in this laſt time, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſtill produce ſome new artifice Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſts, which they alleage to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, ſpeakes only of the ordinary courſe of nature, and of actions, common to all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and to all men. For the production and corruption of ſublunarie bodies, life and death, laughter and teares, proſperity and adverſity, are nothing new under the Sun. But they may object, that Theology is a compleat Science, having all its princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palls, and all its materialls in the Scripture, to which nothing may be added. It is moſt true, but all that which is in the Scripture
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:49144:46"/>hath not as yet been underſtood; ſo then, all that which may bee ſpoken upon the Scripture hath not as yet been ſpoken. There is an infinite number of points in Hiſtory, in the Prophets, in the Morall lawes, in the Ceremonies of the ancient Teſtament, and in the miſteries of Faith, whoſe ſence as yet hath never been intire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dived into. Setting all curioſities apart, 'tis a blockiſh raſhneſſe to believe that Theologie cannot furniſh a ſubject to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny excellent conſiderations as yet never conceived nor underſtood, nor will I ſpeak of the divers Propheſies, whoſe accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment we ſtill expect; and it is not poſſible to ſpeake thereof with ſo much ſufficiencie, as thoſe that ſhall ſee the iſſue, ſo that all is not ſpoken which may belong to this matter; Finally, there is many aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertions which cannot bee pronounced in true tearmes, but in their proper time, as that which our Lord ſaid <hi>(All is fulfill'd)</hi> could nor be ſpoken before. One day it will be ſaid the reſurrection is paſt, which hath not as yet beene ſpoken but by ſome
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:49144:47"/>hereticks, but we muſt paſſe to another head.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. X. <hi>Of Paradoxes, or matters which are ſtrange to the vulgar.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>VVHatſoever is contrary to the common opinion or naturall ſence of men is ordinarily rejected as mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous. Many cannot believe that <hi>Moſes</hi> requiring to be blotted out of the booke of life, or St. <hi>Paul</hi> wiſhing to be made Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema, ſpoke in good earneſt, for all the condition they propoſed to this demand, or for what favour ſoever they could pretend to receive in reſpect of their ſalvation; Much leſſe will they receive that paradoxe grounded upon theſe examples; which is, <hi>That each man ought to preferre the glory of God before his owne proper ſalvation.</hi> Our weakneſſe cannot conceive any thing more feelingly then the particular intereſt of our ſoule, nor have any paſſion ſo ſtrong
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:49144:47"/>as for this ſubject. Nevertheleſſe the the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ory is not leſſe true, although the practice be impoſſible, either in the effect, or in our will; We have ſeen ſome ſcandalized for having heard that it is not permitted to curſe the divell; Which was ſpoken to ſhew by a ſtrong reaſon, that man might not curſe man, were he the moſt deſperate villaine of all the earth; And all the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledictions which a man can pronounce a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the divill, as many doe in vertue of their pretended charge of exorciſts which can be nothing elſe but a frivolous action; nay more, which is an high attempt againſt the juriſdiction of God, which <hi>Michael</hi> the Archangell ſtriving for the body of <hi>Moſes,</hi> durſt never undertake; But popular ſpirits are offended with whatſoever is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to their prejudicate opinions. And nevertheleſſe the Chriſtian religion, if the depths thereof were ſounded full of paradoxes as admirable to thoſe who un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand them as ſtrange to the ignorance of the vulgar.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:49144:48"/>
               <head>CHAP. XI. <hi>Of Problemes, and of their difference, and of morall Problemes in particular.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THere are many points in Theologie, and alſo in other Sciences of which we find no deciſion. Theſe points, becauſe they are not of the eſſence of Faith, and remaine problematicall, are ordinarily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected by the vulgar, as vaine and unprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table. But certainly the Scripture which produceth nothing ſuperfluous ſuggeſts thereby many things unto us; 'tis well knowne that all the difficulties which are found therein, have not as yet beene ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> divers matters remain undecided, and God will have us to exerciſe our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits therein; the leaves namely of the tree of Life have their medicine in them. Theſe queſtions which the Scripture covertly moves, telleth us our ignorance, and ought to be examined for to teach us that our judgement is incapable for to give the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution.</p>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:49144:48"/>
               <p>But indeed there are divers Problemes which may be put into the ranke of cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſities; As the inquiry what is the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of the Angels, and how they ſpeak, ſeeing they have neither tongue nor lungs; Or if in Heaven we ſhall ſpeake the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of the Hebrewes; Or whether the fire of Hell be materiall; or if a man dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a few years ſince, as <hi>Lazarus</hi> ſhould riſe from the dead, whether or no hee ſhould have reaſon to require what belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to him at that time he died, or whether he had left the right, as well as the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. It may be ſome thought of the laſt queſtion, becauſe of ancient Hereticks, who blame the ſecond marriages in taking a pretext, that the firſt marriage did as yet ſubſiſt betwixt the dead man and the living wife, fearing peradventure the dead ſhould ariſe and diſpute the place with his new ſucceſſor, although that the Scripture, namely in expreſſe tearmes hath condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned this folly <hi>Romans</hi> 7. But the queſtions which are moved for to know; What was the ſinne of the evill angels, for which they
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:49144:49"/>were baniſhed from heaven: how long the firſt man remained in the ſtate of Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence; If in the eternall life we ſhall know thoſe we have ſeen in this world; If there be a difference of glory amongſt the bleſſed. and in what place the ſoule is lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in the body, either in the heart, or in the braine, it may be are not ſo vain; lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſide thoſe which are of this nature. Its a curioſity worthy of a Chriſtian to aske what things were the <hi>Vrim</hi> and <hi>Thum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mim</hi> in the breſt-plate of the high Prieſt, if <hi>Jephta</hi> ſacrificed his Daughter, if Saint <hi>Paul</hi> be the author of the Epiſtle to the Hebrews? How many yeares our Lord remained upon the earth from his Nativi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to his Aſcention? Whether faith hath its ſeat in the intellect, or reſides in the will?</p>
               <p>But above all the neceſſity and profit of morall Problemes is evident. I ſpeak not of thoſe which the Caſuiſts have founded upon actions, either impoſſible or frivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, but of queſtions which concernes our inordinary and important occaſions; It is
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:49144:49"/>not ſufficient to ſay, that we have our ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall principles cleare, and out of diſpute, which rules the conſcience in all ſorts of actions; For it is true, that theſe univerſall maximes are like to fixed ſtarres, and have their regular motion; but when we come to hypotheſes and particular occurrences, then they deſcend as in the region of ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments wherein all things are various and turbulent, and where one findes a perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all conflict of reaſons, like to waves drawn by contrary winds; Nor is it ſufficient for a man to alleadge the ſuſpention of his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, when as he doubts the juſtice there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, for feare of corrupting goodneſſe by a ſcrupulous conſcience; For there is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times occaſions in which ſurceaſing, is more criminall then an actuall fault, and whilſt they delay for information ſake, for what they ought to doe, they fall into ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reparable omiſſion; Chriſtian wiſdome ought to prevent theſe perplexities: a man who hath given an oath to his Country to put fire to the powder, and make himſelfe leap into the aire, rather then to render
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:49144:50"/>himſelf to the enemy; hath need to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct his conſcience, before he imbarque himſelf in ſuch a deſigne: but I leave this queſtion, and an infinity of the like nature.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 12. <hi>Of certain caſes of Conſcience which are not as yet reſolved.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NOR is it ſufficient to reply, that there is certain problemes in divers caſes, which look unto the practick, which are not as yet reſolved by the moſt learned, they put the caſe that a man falling into the hands of thieves is conſtrained for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of his life, to ſweare a perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſilence, and to aſſure them as much as lies in him, of impunity. Whether this promiſe may be accompliſhed without of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence or infringed without crime, it is a point which hath not yet been reſolved the reaſons are ſo prevalent on either ſide. Alſo they diſpute, whether a Chriſtian being impriſoned for the faith of the Goſpell
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:49144:50"/>may in conſcience ſeek means to eſcape &amp; come out of the dungeon by breaking of the dores, or by uſing ſome other ſubtilty. Many maintain the negative, and qualifie this evaſion, ſhamefull to the Chriſtian profeſſion, and repugnant to the order of juſtice. Others eſteem it lawfull, and hold that the meanes conducing to our deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance cannot be deſpiſed without tempting God. It hath happened that two being of a contrary Religion, and the Orthodoxall party conſtrained to abandon his dwelling place, his idolatrous wife refuſeth to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low her Chriſtian husband, who asking permiſſion to marry another, the Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gians were divided and of different opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in this reſpect. If there be any thing which ought heretofore to be reſolved, it is this caſe of conſcience.</p>
               <p>The lending of money upon intereſt a queſtion which concerns one of the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary points of particular commerce a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt men; and notwithſtanding it is as yet undecided. For ſome put no diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt a light intereſt, and that
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:49144:51"/>which the Jewes call biting, it being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terdicted by the Law, and others admit it as lawfull in the proportions of equity, as the ſame Law recommends but the diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of a ſolution takes not away the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity and the impoſſibility of it in ſome points takes not away from us the ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after others.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP 13. <hi>Of certain queſtions which are indifferent in which the one ought the rather to be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered then the other.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THere be diſputable matters, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> ar not ſo indifferent or ſo well balla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced but that the weight of the one will turne the ſcales. Its a diſputable point, whether the terreſtriall Paradiſe be as yet ſubſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent. The negative hath more appearance. Its a queſtion not neceſſary, whether the Arch of the alliance was burnt when the <hi>Babylonians</hi> fired the temple. the affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive is the moſt certain, namely we do imploy it to convince of falſeneſſe the hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:49144:51"/>of the <hi>Macchabees,</hi> which relates that this Arch was ſound at the return from the Captivity. Behold here one more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant, to wit, whether the ſpirits, and namely the ſoule of man, are purely imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall eſſences. Certain ancient Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logians followed alſo by ſome moderne Divines, deny it, and give it a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance as that of the aire ſubtil and imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptible, but notwithſtanding in ſome ſort materiall: to which it is very hard to ſubſcribe. This is the moſt conſiderable of all, whether the humane ſoule be immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately produced from God, and by him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed into the body, or whether it draws its effence from his Progenitors, who tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit it to their children by naturall propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, the firſt of theſe two opinions is without doubt the more receiveable and the moſt worthy of a Chriſtian. I ſet aſide the diſputes touching the ſalvation of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> and <hi>Solomon,</hi> in which the moſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable opinion, is alſo moſt certain.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:49144:52"/>
               <head>CHAP. 14. <hi>Indifferent queſtions ſometimes become ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary. Many things are held for prob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lematicall which are not ſo in effect. Problematicall points ought not to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved with the ſame faith, as the articles neceſſary to ſalvation.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF there be any matters which are of ſmall importance they are theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing. What age had <hi>Terah</hi> when <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> was born unto him, <hi>Geneſis</hi> 11.12. how many yeares the <hi>Hebrews</hi> were in <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> Exod. 12. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.17. How many perſons deſcended thither with <hi>Jacob.</hi> Gen. 46.27. Acts 7.14. Theſe points and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other, which we might quote have ſome difficulty. An ignorant will not trouble himſelf therewith, but an Atheiſt will find wherewithall to calumniate the whole Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and the Jews from thence have drawn objections againſt us, crying out the new Teſtament to be falſe, which they preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be contrary to the hiſtory of <hi>Moſes</hi>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:49144:52"/>A Chriſtian is obliged to ſeek inſtruction as well in theſe things as alſo in an infinite of others, to the end that Religion be not blaſphemed through our ignorance.</p>
               <p>On which occaſion you may mark a number of matters, which are Problemati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, rather in opinion, then in effect; I believe that many queſtions which we hold for diſputable, the ſolution thereof is contained in the Scripture, although we find it not therein. Our ignorance is the cauſe that they remain Problematicall which would not be if the Scripture were perfectly underſtood; certainly there is ſome which are not therein decided; we ought not to beſo bold as the Scholaſticks who have diſputed if the raviſhing of S. <hi>Paul</hi> into the third heaven was in body or in ſpirit onely. They might be aſſured nor to find the ſolution thereof. But on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide it's a great temerity to hold all for undecided in the Scripture, becauſe we cannot reſolve it.</p>
               <p>In the mean time there is no reaſon for us to imbrace with an equall ſtableneſſe
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:49144:53"/>of belief, the points which are as yet Prob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lematicall unto us, as thoſe of which we have a full aſſurance.</p>
               <p>It is moſt worthy to be believed that the Virgin never had any other children then he for whom all ages call her bleſſed. But this point is not of the ſame quality as thoſe whoſe demonſtration is cleare un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dubitable and neceſſary.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 15. <hi>Of thoſe who will know nothing but what is found in the Scripture.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WIthout derogating from the Scripture the perfect rule of faith as well as of manners, we ſay there is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers matters not contained therein, whoſe ignorance would be ſhamefull and unfit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to a Chriſtian capable of inſtruction. I ſpeak not here of many natural principles which the Scripture expreſſeth not, as not to know that two contradictions cannot be true, or that the whole is greater, then a part under colour that the Scriptures
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:49144:53"/>ſpeaks not of it, ſhould be a criminall brutality. The Scripture teaches not natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Notions, but preſuppoſeth them as manifeſt, becauſe it ſpeaks to men, not to ſtones. I leave divers hiſtories and prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, as are the works of <hi>Daniel,</hi> the drying up of the river <hi>Euphrates</hi> in the <hi>Apocalips</hi> and a number of others which is impoſſible to underſtand without the knowledge of many things which the Scripture teacheth not. The Paſſage of the Iſraelites through the red ſea. The darkneſſe happening at the death of our Lord are acknowledged to be miraculous, becauſe they came in a time that they could not be produced by natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall cauſes, which was the reaſon that the Scripture paſſeth it under ſilence. All the predictions which have come to paſſe ſince the cloſing of the new Teſtament ſhow not their accompliſhment but in humane hiſtories: Nay all theſe propheſies are fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally reduced into hiſtories, which are not found in the Scripture.</p>
               <p>But I will onely touch one point or two which conſiſt not but onely in act. He
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:49144:54"/>who would believe the temple of <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> is as yet ſtanding? that the Jews ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice therein? and that the other legall ceremonies are practiſed as if their Repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick as yet ſubſiſted would be culpable of a very groſſe error, and notwithſtanding the hiſtory of the ceſſation of ſacrifices is not to be read in the Scripture, it teacheth us that the Leviticall ſacrifices were abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by right but as then in act. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe this actuall abolition came ſince ſo advantageouſly for the Chriſtians, that one cannot be ignorant thereof without manifeſt carelesneſſe. Alſo we do not learn in the Scripture, that there be as yet<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Jews in the world: and nevertheleſſe it would b a blockiſh ſtupidity to be ignorant of the ſubſiſtance of that nation, whoſe miſery verifies the threatnings of our ſaviour upon them, and whoſe converſion we do as yet expect. But above all it would be an igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance worthy of reproach to put in indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferency how many ages we ought to count ſince the birth of Chriſt. A man who ſhould not know whether there were
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:49144:54"/>more then two hundred yeares ſince Jeſus Chriſt was borne, ſhould be unworthy the name of a Chriſtian, although that the ſupputation be a matter of Chronologie, which is not deduced in the Scripture, but increaſeth day by day.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XVI. <hi>Of thoſe which ſtudie nothing but controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, what ſort of controverſies may teach us moſt doctrine: What points of doctrine are the moſt difficult amongſt Chriſtians. What expedient may weake ones take in the higheſt queſtions. A rule which is not to be found, but in the reformed Religion. Of Miracles. Of Martyres. Concerning the queſtion where was the Church before the Reformation.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SOme ſeek no other inſtruction but that of controverſies; a ſtudie truly which is neceſſary for to furniſh Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotes in places, or in times infected with hereſies: But yet it is incapable to give
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:49144:55" rendition="simple:additions"/>unto the ſoule a full reflection. He ſhould truly be a foole, who would take no other nouriſhment, but from the Treacle or the Rubarbe. Controverſies ſhewes not the whole body of Religion, but the parts thereof which are in diſpute. And this is but by accident: For our faith is affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, not negative. And our knowledge hath for its object the evidence of truths, not the diſguiſing of errors. Who would come by this way to a more univerſall knowledge of religion, he muſt ſtudy not only all whatſoever wee diſpute with the Roman Catholicks, but alſo whatſoever the Chriſtian Church debates againſt an infinite of Sects, who rob her of her title; nay more, all the differencies which wee have to decide with the Jewes. Mahome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans, Indians, and other Pagans, and that which is worſe with a multitude of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts.</p>
               <p>If there be a controverſie in which a Chriſtian armed to the proofe againſt blaſphemies, may learne rare and excellent things, 'tis in that which we have with the
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:49144:55" rendition="simple:additions"/>Jewes, I underſtand for to have an exact knowledge, and not to conſider only the trunke, but alſo all the branches; the juyce and the marrow from the loweſt of the rootes, to the higheſt of the leaves. To ſee the depth of this controverſie, is more painfull then all the others. It hath but ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry few Philoſophicall arguments; All therein is drawne from the deep fountaines of the ancient teſtament, and you muſt lift all the curtaines of the Tabernacle, and paſſe through many vailes, before that one can ſee the holieſt of holies. This was the exerciſe of the firſt Chriſtians. For their firſt diſputes began by the Jewes, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting neceſſity which obligeth us to turn head to other adverſaries, this controverſie would be more fruitfull then any other.</p>
               <p>There are two ſorts of matter in which lies the hardeſt controverſies which be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Chriſtians, and the moſt difficult to manage; 1. Thoſe which touch the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of God, as the Previſion or Preſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, Prudence, <hi>Predeſtination, Reprobati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> &amp;c. Secondly, Thoſe which concernes
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:49144:56" rendition="simple:additions"/>the qualities of the ſoule, be it in Nature, or be it in Grace, Free-will, certainty of Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The reaſon why theſe two points are more difficult then the others, is evident in reſpect of the firſt.</p>
               <p>Divine decrees are infinitely diſtant from our ſight, as being elevated above all times and incloſed in a volume of which we ſee nothing but a few characters hard to be diſcerned at ſo great a diſtance. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny who thinke they read there diſtinctly, draw moſt dangerous conſtructions. But it is a wonder in the other point, that ſo many difficulties are found, ſeeing that the ſubject is ſo neare our eyes, nay, that it is within our ſelves. Our intellect is in trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to know whether our intellect and the will are faculties really different. Whether granting the judgement of the Intellect, the will muſt neceſſary follow: or if it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines in Balance, and in power to ſuſpend its action. If our faith be placed in the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellect, or in our will: Our ſoule ſo little knowes thereof, that ſhe knowes not where to find her ſelfe, being ignorant whether
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:49144:56" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſhe reſides in the blood, or in any other particular part of the body, or whether ſhe be univerſally diffuſed through all the parts thereof. The proximitie it ſelfe of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, is the cauſe of this difficulty. The ſoule no more then the eye cannot ſee it ſelfe, except it be by a very obſcure refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and that falſe to, for the moſt part, which we call indirect knowledge; For to diſturbe the ſpirits of the common peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ye need but to ſet them on theſe two points, which many have choſen expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as being full of Labirinths.</p>
               <p>He who hath not been acquainted with theſe ſlights, ought to remember that in each controverſie truth lodgeth in a center, to which ought to bend all matters which are in diſpute. In theſe differences which concerne the will of God towards man, or the will of man towards God (for all the controverſies of Election, of univerſall grace, of free will, of perſeverance, and ſuch like, may have relation to theſe two things) theſe maximes ought to be the center, to wit, that the glory of all good belongs to
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:49144:57" rendition="simple:additions"/>God. That whatſoever is ill proceeds from man. We muſt not attribute to God the ill that proceeds from man. Nor to man the good which proceeds from God. One cannot take from God the ſmalleſt part of his glory without raviſhing it intirely, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that it is indiviſible as a point that admits no parting. Commutative juſtice cannot happen to be in God. The creature attributing unto God all the good which is in her, cannot faile in exceſſe, nor incurre any danger thereby, but in attributing ſome portion thereof to himſelfe, he may runne ſome hazard. In theſe principles which are as undoubtable as familiar, as they may eaſily reſolve all the ſubrilties, will they, or nill they, which may be produced on the one ſide, or the other; And the weakeſt Chriſtian taking heed to the lines which end not in this center, or fall aſide, will ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily judge that they are irregular.</p>
               <p>This conſtant and univerſall rule may be applyed to all fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>octrine, <hi>John</hi> 7.18 and I dare ſay, that of all religions which are in the world, there is none but the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:49144:57" rendition="simple:additions"/>which attributes to God the glory of all good, eſpecially in the ſalvation of man. And certainly, there is not one of the others, but makes profeſſion to attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to God this glory; but examining them nearly, you ſhall not find any but that take away ſome part, to make thereof a preſent to man what they avow in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, they ſteale by retaile, or deny it by their conſequences to hinder God from poſſeſſing of it in effect: As to the reſt the common people ought to diſtinguiſh the certaine and the infallible propoſitions from prejudicate opinions, which may be diſputable. It's a common opinion, that there are no miracles wrought in the world, and that there ſhall be never more. This negative is uncertaine, and the proofe neither aſſured or neceſſary. When all the miracles which the Jeſuits doe atteſt to have bin wrought in the midſt of the Indies ſhould be true, they would not conclude the leaſt of their errors, no more then the annuall miracle at the poole of <hi>Shiloa</hi> gave authority to Phariſaiſme. Much leſſe can
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:49144:58" rendition="simple:additions"/>they draw any conſequence from the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdome which ſome of them have ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the hands of Indian Idolaters. Their Martyrs will never goe peere with ours. When a man ſuffers death under an opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion that it will be meritorious, I am a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid he is a Martyr of his owne merit, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then that of Chriſts, the puniſhment gives him no higher a tytle then that of his beliefe, or of his profeſſion.</p>
               <p>There is as yet one point more which we may as yet remarke. To the queſtion where the Church was before the laſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, we ordinarily anſwer that it was in Poperie, as if Poperie were all the world, whereas it holds but one little cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. As if the Church could not be in <hi>Africa,</hi> or in <hi>Aſia,</hi> where Popery was not. In effect we deprive our ſelves of a very ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie anſwer, and doe a great injury to an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finity of Grecian, Arminian, and Abiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin Churches, and others in which the Church of God reſided; Churches who confeſſe the Trinitie of Perſons, the Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the two Natures in Chriſt, and all
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:49144:58"/>the points of Mediation. Churches which ſeek their juſtification by faith in the righteouſneſſe of Jeſus Chriſt onely: Churches which practiſe the ſame Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments with us, and admit no other eating of the body of Chriſt but that which is ſpirituall: Churches, in which nothing is wanting that is eſſential to the faith, but if corruptions have made them deformed 'tis not ſo exorbitant but that the Church might as well ſubſiſt therein as in the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man which held nothing but on part of the Weſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 17. <hi>The converſion of a Romane Catholick is now more difficult then in the beginning of the Reformation.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE Reformed Church had in times paſt, enough to open the doore to Empires, and to whole nations, who preſented themſelves in crowds to enter in, at this day it is a wonder to heare of any one Proſelyte. Mens judgements vary upon
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:49144:59"/>the cauſes of ſo great a difference, That novelty provoked the ſpirits to harken to this Religion, ſo full of admirable Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxes, whereas now uſe hath brought in the diſguſt. That the Reformation came when the <hi>Vatican</hi> inſolently tyranniſed the Potentates, and the people glad to ſhake off the yoke, and that the behaviour of the firſt reformed had a luſtre which rendered his Religion amiable. That their zeale which let this Religion at ſo high a priſe, alighted in many a violent paſſion to ſeeke this treaſure. That perſecution whoſe <hi>anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peristaſis</hi> redoubled their zeal, hath more augmented the Church, then proſperity the moſt triumphant. Like the Ark, which did more miracles whilſt that it wandered in the wilderneſse under a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilion of goates hair, more then after when it was, placed under the wainſcot of Cedar laid over with plaites of Gold. That the miraculous ſubſiſting of the Church a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong ſo many powerfull oppoſirions ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhed the eyes of all the world, ſeeing a burning buſh, and yet remain unconſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:49144:59"/>That the voice of the Martyrs ſhook the priſons, and the tribunalls, the fires in which they were ſacrificed ſerved for lights to ſhow many the way to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. And finally God which makes the winds blow in ſuch places and ſeaſons as ſeems good to him hath bounded the courſe of his grace, and forbidden his word to paſse further. But to this one may adde that the prudence of the Romane Clergy hath choaked divers abuſes, and ſent to the Aſſiſe many blaſphemies which made the moſt ſtupid to abhorre them. And above all, time hath furniſhed them with many ſleights (unknown to their forefathers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing buried in ignorance <hi>of learning</hi>) for to ſhun the moſt manifeſt truths, and give a colour to opinions the moſt abſurd, ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending the judgements of the cleareſt ſighted, between the miracles of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the cunning of the inchanters. Finally they had many principalls, and interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which they have left, acknowledging that they were contrary to themſelves: in times paſt they were content to make
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:49144:60"/>the Scripture their judge; at this day they accuſe it of incompetency and decline its juridiction. This principall being reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted it is more difficult to reduce a Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Catholick to the Orthodox Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 18. <hi>Why the converſion of a Jew at this day, then it was at the beginning of Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THeſe reaſons are alſo thoſe in part of the pertinacity of the Jews if e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver this nation ought to render it ſelf to the obedience of the faith, it is at this day that it ought to be a diſperſion of more then 1500 yeares, far longer then all precedent calamities, and in which they have neither had temple nor ſacrifice to expiate their ſinnes. The vain expectation of their pretended Meſſias ſo oftentimes fruſtrated, ſince the prefixed tearme of his coming; of which they know not what
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:49144:60"/>to think. The confuſion happened in their genealogies, ſo great that namely, when their Meſſias ſhould come, they cannot know him, not being able to mark any fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily that's deſended from <hi>David.</hi> Theſe teſtimonies I ſay of their fooliſh hope ought to make them leave their ſtubborn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes more then ever. And notwithſtanding their obſtinacy was never ſo great. Nay it is now harder to convert a Jew, then in times paſt before ſo long a lapſe of time which as yet makes them requoil farther from their pretenſions. The weakneſſe of their cauſe hath made them ingenious to ſtrengthen themſelves therein. Since the ſubverſion of their Republick ſome yeares after the aſcention of our Lord, perceiving that the time belied their hope, and being aſhamed not to ſee ſome glimpſe which might promiſe them the effect; on the other ſide ſeeing that Chriſtianity ſpread it ſelf farre and near principall under the Empire of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the great, they ſought all the meanes they could imagine to retain their nation ſtill in their blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:49144:61"/>Now in as much as that they were condemned in their own Maximes, and namely by the interpretation of their <hi>Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bins.</hi> They took counſell how to abrogate them, and to ſubſtitute ohers of a contrary opinion to them ſo then, ſo that where a paſſage of the ancient Teſtament ſpeaking of the Meſſias, was taken in its true ſence by the ancient Jewes, the Modern have changed the expoſition. Our Lord for to prove Chriſt to be more then man alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth that <hi>David</hi> called him Lord, alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to this purpoſe <hi>Pſalm</hi> 110. this paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage was not then in diſpute. For the Jews then of that time confeſſed that thoſe tearms could not have relation but to the Meſſias. But thoſe at this day overthrow this interpretarion which their forefathers did agree unto without reply, ſo that up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all thoſe paſſages which the Apoſtle ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in favour of Chriſt, the Jews diſputed the application rather then the explication but now they conteſt both, having char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged their principalls. There is another trick which they uſe to make Chriſtian
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:49144:61"/>religion to be ſuſpected both to their nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and alſo to all others hath been to ſeek out all the paſſages of the new Teſtament which ſeemes to differ from the ancient in ſome hiſtoricall circumſtances, as in the date of yeares, in the names of places, in the numbring of perſons, and ſuch like, pretending by this difference to convince the Apoſtolicall writings of falſhood, and ſo by conſequence to annihilate C riſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 19. <hi>Why the opinions the moſt erronious are main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained with greater obſtinacy, then thoſe which are leſſe abſurd. The plea of theſe which burnt their children. Pretexts for tranſubſtantiation.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe more monſtrous is the errour the more pertinacious is the belief when once it hath taken place in the ſpirit; the reaſon is becauſe the fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoods the moſt enormous are made im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:49144:62"/>by the higheſt pretexts of truth and are not authoriſed but by the moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted maximes of religion under the colour of this ſoveraigne power<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, they make men renounce their judgement of reaſon, nay more diſavow their own pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſences. If ever there were an error inca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable it was the impiety of the Iſraelites who burnt their own children as a ſacrifice pleaſing to God. Nevertheleſſe neither nature which cried out againſt thoſe hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, nor the threatnings fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heaven which condemned them could not hinder their practiſe. But it needs muſt be that ſome vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent paſſion which brake in ſunder the ſtrongeſt chains of naturall affections was moved with ſome powerfull engine, cloak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed over with ſome very ſpecious pretext. Their apology might be that the chiefeſt good of man conſiſts in the remiſſion of his ſinnes; that this remiſſion could not be without the effuſion of blood. That it were a folly to go about to appeaſe God by the blood of beaſts, and therefore ſome humane ſacrifice muſt be offered. That
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:49144:62"/>this ſacrifice ought to be innocent; and that a greater innocence could not be found, then in a little infant. That to be of the proper ſubſtance of the man which did preſent it, and ſo it was neceſsary that his offering ſhould be offered in expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation. But if the ſacrifice ought to be but Euchariſticall, then it were but to mock God, to preſent him a calf or a pigeon, his Majeſty requiring more noble offerings; nay more demanding our own bowels, and that they knew not how to offer him a more precious preſent then the life of their own children. Under this pretext and ſuch like, this abomination paſsed for the moſt ardent piety which a man may ſhow to God, equalliſing or rather ſurpaſſing all which the Scripture extolls in <hi>Abraham</hi> for an action of this quality: So that the exceſse of errour augments the perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
               <p>The article of tranſubſtantiation is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced under the name of the moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and moſt dreadfull miſterie of all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, bearing upon its front the expreſse
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:49144:63"/>words of the ſonne of God, whoſe preſence is fearfull to the Angels, arming it ſelfe with the power of his omnipotency, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſing within its titles, all the Majeſty of heaven, and the ſalvation of the whole world. By how much the repreſentation of this opinion is prodigious, by ſo much the more it makes them believe it miſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</p>
               <p>From thence it comes that that belief is maintained with more pertinacity then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny error whoſe abſurdity is leſse apparant. Alſo the believing hereof is eſteemed ſo much the more meritorious, by how much leſse the object is to be believed, as indeed that man who firmly believes this tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation ſhould have (were it true) more faith then ever had all the Patriarks and Apoſtles together.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="section">
            <pb n="119" facs="tcp:49144:63"/>
            <head>The third Section.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER 1. <hi>What manner of knowledge or inſtruction is moſt naturall to the vulgar.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>WO men may know one and the ſame truth, but in divers manners. A Country man may know that an Eclypſe ought to happen on ſuch a day, having read it in an Almanack; but that is not called Science as an Aſtronomer who knows by demonſtration foreſeeing the Eclypſe in his cauſes. He is not learned in religion who knows all the matters, but he that knows them in the manner, they ought to be known; on which many faults are to be obſerved.</p>
               <p>There are two traditions or wayes of
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:49144:64"/>inſtruction, on which the vulgar repoſe themſelves. Sentences and generall propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions. 2 Hiſtories, in theſe two conſiſts almoſt all the knowledge of the common people. As for the firſt head the ignorant content themſelves to know the generali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, becauſe the intelligence of particular points requires a ſharper ſight and a more fixed contemplation. Its eaſier to an Idiot to ſay <hi>Theſe Things,</hi> then to reſtrain this generality to its ſpecies, to know how to give each one of them its proper name. To the other the inſtruction which is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them by hiſtory pleaſeth them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of its facility, for it conſiſts in acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and circumſtances perceptible to the imagination; ſo that all their knowledge lodgeth either in copious generalities or in the ſingle <hi>individuums:</hi> but the points which are as it were <hi>mediums</hi> between theſe two wearies more the ſpirit obliging them to reaſon, and to take the meaſure, weight and number, and the names of all things. This is the cauſe the vulgar caſt it off. In the mean time many are Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxall
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:49144:64"/>in the generality of a point, who erre groſſely in the particulars thereof; witneſſe the article of providence upon which the common people will give a cleare opinion in reſpect of the generality of this doctrine; but in the particular points imagine a world of abſurdities.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 2. <hi>Of the ſuperficiall knowledge of each point of Of religion. Of their definitions, and of their exact Knowledge. An example in the doctrine of the Euchariſt.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE ignorance of generall as well as particular points proceed from this, that popular ſpirits learn an infinity of deſcriptions, but very few defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions; I ſpeak not in favour of ſubtil and artificiall definitions of which every one is not capable. But certainly it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to have the true knowledge of a point without knowing how to mark and define the eſſence, if not exactly, yet at leaſt, very near the truth.</p>
               <pb n="122" facs="tcp:49144:65"/>
               <p>When a man can ſay ſinne is the poyſon of the ſoule, and knows how to give it a hundred epithites of this ſort, yet hath he not learnt what ſinne is, this ignorance is entertained by a multitude of Preachers who are content to declaim by deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and abundance of metahpots never ſhowing but the ſuperficies of matters in ſtead of ſetting forth the dimenſions. I leave the points which are elevated above all definition. The imagination of Idiots who not underſtanding what is properly that eternity, although they know that God hath neither beginning nor end, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve him nevertheleſſe to have more age then he had foure thouſand yeares ſince. This point and many others are not the mark at which we ſhoot. I could ſhow that the greateſt part of our differencies proceed from the ignorance of definiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. If the Romiſh Church comprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed interceſſion to be a ſacerdotall act, and that Chriſt prayes in quality of a ſoveraign Prieſt dead for us; and this function con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in the comparition of his perſon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  <pb n="123" facs="tcp:49144:65"/>She would never tranſport to others the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of interceſſor. But to make you ſee how many excellent matters the exact intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of one point furniſheth in reſpect of a ſuperficiall knowledge, we will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce only one example. In the words of the Lord in the Euchariſt, the moſt ignorant underſtand ſufficiently, that the fleſh of Chriſt therein is preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted unto us as meat, and not only in this reſpect, but as meat of ſacrifice, for it is properly in this quality that it is offered unto us. And the termes of our Lord carry a manifeſt alluſion to the fleſh of ſacrifices which they gave to eat to thoſe for whom it had been ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. A meat which the Jewes becauſe of its importancy preferred before all other a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liments. But you muſt know they did not participate but of the Euchariſticall ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices: for the people eat not the fleſh of the ſacrifices of expiation although that they were offered for them, the ſacrificers onely did participate thereof. Nay more, a ſacrificer when he offered for his own ſins had no part in the ſacrifice, but was to
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:49144:66"/>burn it intirely. And which is more, in the ſolemne expiation, in which the blood of beaſts was carried into the tabernacle for the univerſall remiſſion of ſinnes, no man might taſt of the fleſh of the ſacrifice, the law commanding that it ſhould be carried out of the camp far from the people, and there conſumed in fire. In brief, it was a maxime in the law, that none of thoſe for whom the ſacrifice of expiation was offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſhould eat thereof. But our Lord by a diſpoſition new, and unknown to the law, preſents us to eat of the fleſh of the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of expiation, the body which hath been delivered for our ſinnes. For the law forbidding thoſe which were culpable to participate of the expiations ſhewed the nullity of them; and taught that thoſe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices were unprofitable, ſeeing that thoſe in whoſe favour they were offered had no nouriſhment by them: But Jeſus Chriſt ſhews that his ſacrifice is fruitfull, ſeeing that ſinners participate thereof, marking in evident tearmes the difference which we ſee between the blood of the new
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:49144:66"/>alliance given for drink, and the bloud of Legall ſacrifices whoſe participation was rigorouſly forbidden; the law forbidding to drink any blood gives this reaſon, that the blood was ſhed for the expiation of ſinnes, and ſo ought not to be imployed for nouriſhment; to the contrary, our Lord invites us to drink his blood, becauſe that it is ſhed for the remiſſion of ſinnes; Imploying (for to oblige us to the partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of blood) the ſame reaſon for which it was interdicted in the law. This conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration may furniſh many others where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to comprehend the ſubject of the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:49144:67"/>
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>Of the distinction, conjunction, and Aran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of points of religion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe beaſts which divide not the hooſe are uncleane by the Law; The reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of a man which knowes not how to diſtinguiſh the points thereof cannot be pure. Diſtinctions which conſiſt in vain ſubtilties, in diviſions, and fooliſh ſubdivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, to the cleaving of a haire, who un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der colour of narrowly ſifting them, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the moſt ſolid matters into duſt and atomes, which in ſtead of clearing the ſight, gathers up nothing but duſt to caſt into the eyes of the ſimple; overturning the ſoundeſt propoſitions, under colour of upholding them, which under pretext of directing the ſpirit, ſhewes it ſo many dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent paths, that it knowes not which to reſolve on; theſe diſtinctions tend not to our end. On the other ſide the vulgar ſcornes many diſtinctions, the ignorance
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:49144:67"/>of which is ſubject to a thouſand errors. An idiot which knowes little or nothing of the difference between Faith and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity cannot underſtand the point of Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, for if Faith and Charitie are but one ſelfe-ſame thing, we are then ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by Charity, which is a pernicious conſequence.</p>
               <p>But if one ſhould aske why Charity can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not juſtifie as well as Faith, the reaſon is manifeſt to him who knowes how Faith and Charity are diſtinguiſhed. The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty of Faith is to receive. The property of Charity is to give. By Faith we receive God, giving himſelfe to us with all his benefits. By Charity we offer our ſelves unto him, and all that is in us. Now God would not have us juſtified by giving to him, for then grace would be no more grace (and mans boaſting ſhould not be excluded) but by the only receiving and acceptation of the righteouſneſſe which he preſents us; and this receiving is an act of Faith, of which Charity is incapable. The common people alſo confound the
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:49144:68" rendition="simple:additions"/>legall righteouſneſſe with the Evangelical, ſanctification with juſtification, not ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king heed that in the contexture of the ſame paſſage there is found a word of the Law, and a word of the Goſpell chained together, but which ought to be carefully diſtinguiſhed; As in theſe words of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>If thou wilt enter into life, keepe the commandements;</hi> this was the Law which ſpake, and not the Goſpell, nay, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of the Law are mortall to whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever accepts the condition.</p>
               <p>He who tranſgreſſeth one point of the Law, tranſgreſſeth the whole Law; As he which ſtrikes the heart only, or the lungs only, or the braines only, doth for all that give a mortall attaint to the body. So all the parts of faith make but one undivided body, and he which is ignorant only of one, is ignorant of all the others. In the meane time, he who would examine the popular ſpirits ſhould find few who know their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion intirely; few there be whoſe know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is not deficient in ſome point: but the knowledge it ſelfe of all the parts of
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:49144:68"/>religion doth not as yet ſerve to a true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence thereof, if one knowes not their conjunctions, their relations and their cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondencies. All the points of religion are relatives. Sometimes a point conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the conjunction of another carries aſence contrary to that which it had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſeparated. The Law contemplated a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part is a letter which kills: joyned with the Goſpell is a Reſtaurative to the ſoule. Faith in its abſolute eſſence is a part of Sanctification, and in this quality juſtifies not a ſinner: in its relation to Chriſt, it is the inſtrument of our Juſtification. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the relation which the parts of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion have the one to the other, each one of them, and altogether have relation to one Totall, as members to a body, whoſe ſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture reſults from their compoſition, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portions, ligaments and order. But many know all the parts of religion, who under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand nothing in the totall, becauſe they ſee all the pieces thereof only in detaile, but not in their conjunction.</p>
               <p>A man who ſhould know the number
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:49144:69"/>of all the kindes of creatures the eſſential forme of each one of them, their proper cauſes, the particular end, and the effect to which they ſerve, the ranke, and place which they hold in the world, would reade as in a booke, for each creature is as a cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, having its forme, and its diſtinct propriety, and altogether being ranged in divers places produce ſuch a frame of words which are intelligible by us, if our ignorance confound them not. He that knoweth the points of Religion, but is ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant in what order he ought to ranke them, reſembleth an ideot who underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the found of every Letter of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phabet, without knowing how to join them to make entire words thereof. Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as it is in the knowledge of many, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth in the multitude of matters confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly heaped together in the mind, without ſymmetry, or proportio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, without any form either of building or body, the head and feet being confounded. Some of our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies concern the ſame order, and rank of points. The Romane Catholicks co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:49144:69" rendition="simple:additions"/>to contend with us, begin voluntari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with the queſtion of the Church, giving it the higheſt place, to the end they may make it paſſe as a rule, and principle of faith. But the Article of the Church hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not the firſt rank in the Creed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IIII. <hi>Of thoſe which believe the truth, by vertue of a falſe principle, or of ſome paſsage of Scripture which toucheth not the queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MAny believe the truth by a falſe faith. The Turk believes God, the creation, providence, the immortality of the ſoul, Chriſt born of a virgin, a great Prophet, and the word of God, becauſe the Alchoran ſaith it. Theſe points are true in themſelves: but the belief which he hath thereby cannot be formally true, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it depends on a falſe principle. Truth may not be believed for a lyes ſake.</p>
               <p>One may not commend them which
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:49144:70"/>endeavour to amplifie the Oracles of the <hi>Sybills,</hi> to the end they may make them ſpeak more advantagiouſly in favour of the Chriſtian Religion. Nor the pious frauds of them which under colour of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the immortality of the ſoul, have ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed fabulous apparitions. It importeth not onely what we believe, but alſo why we believe it. A man which believeth there is a God, becauſe Philoſophy, or na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall reaſon teacheth him ſo, hath not a Theologick faith, although the beliefe which he hath touching God, be true in it ſelf, and in its principles.</p>
               <p>He that believeth all the Articles of Chriſtianity, becauſe great Doctors be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve them, or onely becauſe the Church holds them for true, hath built his faith up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on mans teſtimonie. 'Tis a complaint of a perſon eminent in humane learning, that being Orthodox in the Article of Chriſts Divinity, notwithſtanding in his interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and Parapraſes upon the new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, he did enervate, or allude, aſmuch as was poſſible for him, all the moſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:49144:70"/>paſſages which authoriſe the beliefe of this point. But on the other ſide, the world is full of people which upon every ſort of matter alledge a multitude of Texts, though oft times the twentieth part ſuit not to the ſubject. They which believe a truth, but ground it upon a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of Scripture, which maketh not to the purpoſe, believe the truth falſely. That which they believe is very true: but that by vertue whereof they believe it, is not ſo. For the Scripture ill applyed is no more Scripture, but a perverting thereof: al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be alleadged to prove the truth which it teacheth in other paſſages. And 'twere to be wiſhed that many would bring hither as much feare and diſcretion, as they abound in impertinent quotations. But the vulgar often ſuffer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelves to be led more by paſſages which come by the by, then by thoſe which lead ſtraight to the mark. I have ſeene a man which could never be brought from the Invocation of Saints, for any Text alleadged unto him, unleſſe when one quoted to him the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:49144:71" rendition="simple:additions"/>of <hi>Eſay</hi> 63. <hi>ver.</hi> 16. which notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding is not the moſt concluding of all thoſe which are made uſe of in this contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie. A Rabbin converted to the faith, and who had writ againſt thoſe of his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, found the Trinity and the two na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of Chriſt in the foure Hebrew let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the word Jehovah; And made al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt more eſteem of this Cabbaliſtick proof, then of all the paſſages of the old Teſtament, infinitely more cleare, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe upon this ſubject. That which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines to be ſaid requires another Paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Every point of Religion hath its peculiar reaſons, examples, and conſiderations to this purpoſe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ALL the points of Religion, and all the leſſer branches of them, have eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one their particular reaſon.</p>
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:49144:71"/>
               <p>And the Scripture ſaith not only that it is ſo, but alſo how and why it is ſo.</p>
               <p>It gives us not ſimple poſitions, but teacheth by demonſtration, and arguments, even to the reſolving of objections which may be moved to the contrary. This is not then ſufficient, when a man knows all his Religion by Propoſitions or Maximes, though conceived in proper Scripture tearms, if he know not alſo the particular reaſon of every one of them. And to render a reaſon of our faith, is not only to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadge the Scripture, which affirms ſuch or ſuch points, but alſo to ſhew why theſe points which the Scripture affirmeth are ſuch, and that they are the cauſes of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one of them in particular. Divinity is all full of demonſtrative arguments. They which have but a naked knowledge of concluſions, ſee well the face and exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſhape of Religion: But the beating of its arteries, the ſpirit which moves it, and the faculties which ſtir within it, are viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to them who know the reaſons where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with it is animated.</p>
               <pb n="136" facs="tcp:49144:72" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>It is not to the purpoſe to alleadge, that one ought not to demand a reaſon what God ſaith, and that it is enough to believe what the Scripture pronounceth is true. This objection is of value as touching points the ſearch whereof is forbidden us; as Why God ſheweth mercy more to one then to another, and for other matters which we may call tranſcendent, which God hath bounded with praecipices, &amp; en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vironed with high barricadoes which hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der us from entring in thereat. But in thoſe whereof the Scripture teaches us the reaſons, 'tis a fooliſh modeſty to reaſon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his command which obligeth us to learn them. Nay this is a manifeſt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogance, to will the ignorance of thoſe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons the Scripture gives us thereof, under pretence of believing the Scripture ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply. For the Scripture it ſelf teacheth us to reaſon upon many points infinitely rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed above us. When it is asked Why God permitted that ſinne ſhould enter into the world, though it were in his power to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it? Many reaſons of this permiſſion
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:49144:72" rendition="simple:additions"/>may be found, full of excellent doctrine; and ſaving the matters we have excepted, there is not any point of Religion, nay any particle, whereof one may not find ſome reaſon, either expreſt in the Scripture, or duly averred by lawfull conſequences, or reſulting from the property of the ſubject. If there be any thing which ſeemeth to be out of all enquiry they are the principles of nature. As for example, The prohibitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of marriage between brother and ſiſter, is the voice of nature, which hath no need to be propped with reaſons, ſince it is reaſon it ſelf. And though one may always ſay that the Scripture would oblige men to ſearch the alliance of the remoteſt races, to the end that the affections, &amp; correſpondencies of humane ſocietie might be multiplied: w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> would not be, if marriages ſhould be alwayes contracted within the ſame fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Which would by this ſhame reſtrain the licenſe which might grow from the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cility of their converſation. That ſo many naturall relations met in one man, which might have brought the title of father and
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:49144:73"/>uncle together, would have brought a thouſand confuſions in the world. That the ſame proximity being diſputed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them which are of the ſame blood, would have produced divers ſtrifes in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, for the reaſon as that of the ſtraight line, which oblige the brother to marry his half ſiſter: that the woman who in caſe of injury, or diſſertion might find a refuge with their brothers, had loſt his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge if the brotherhood had been confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the marriage. And other reaſons which one might alleadge for this law.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP VI. <hi>Of the exerciſe of the mind in every point of Religion. The default of the vulgar, and of preachers herein. The Scripture ſpeaks by proofs.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>GOd would that our knowledge ſhould be diſcurſive in part; and that this faculty of the ſoule, which paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:49144:73"/>from one ſubject to another, for to diſcern them, compare them together, and give judgement thereof, might alſo be ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified by this exerciſe in matters of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. But becauſe it is more difficult to reaſon upon a point, then to conceive it nakedly and barely; the common people is contented to heare that ſuch a thing is true, or good, or juſt, without ſearching why or how it is ſuch. The ignorant love onely to heare a thing affirmed, or denyed: inſomuch that to the underſtanding of a propoſition or aſſertion thus naked, there is need of but a bare apprehenſion, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of words, without other trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of mind. Whereupon they are delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in maximes, and proverbs, becauſe it is not needfull to conceive the ſenſe thereof, eaſie to whoſoever underſtandeth the words. For 'tis to be preſuppoſed they are grounded on reaſon, and 'tis enough to hold them for true, without any other form of enquiry. This ſame facility is the cauſe we have more talkers then preachers.</p>
               <p>Provided they ſtretch out a point by a
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:49144:74"/>long train of equivalent tearms, that they delate a text into Paraphraſes, that they heape togeather a great maſſe of ſentences of Scripture, they think they have worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly handled, and the vulgar abide therewith ſatisfied. But the interpretation thereof requires much more then this. Certainly Jeſus Chriſt himſelfe, and the moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent inſtruments which have ſpok by his ſpirit, have not contented themſelves to pronounce the affirmative, or negative up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any point, but beſides have ſhewed the reaſons thereof. If they teach that the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God ought to be ſpirituall; they give this proofe thereof, to wit that God is a ſpirit. If the alleadge to make the Jewes ſee that the <hi>Meſſias</hi> ought to die, and riſe again, the words of the Pſalmeſt, <hi>thou ſhalt not ſuffer thy holy one to ſee corruption:</hi> they frame thereof an argument which imports that this Oracle cannot relate but to <hi>David,</hi> or to Chriſt, that the body of <hi>David</hi> had notoriouſly felt the ſame cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption which death brings to other men<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> So that this prophecy could not belong
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:49144:74"/>but to Chriſt. If they ſay that man is not juſtified by the Law. they prove it by the end of the Law, which is to manifeſt ſinne. If they declare that Circumciſion doth not juſtifie; they ſhew it by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>Abraham,</hi> who was juſtified be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was circumciſed: So that his cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion being after his juſtification could not have produced it. If they affirm that there was a Law before that of <hi>Moſes,</hi> they argue that where there is no law, there is no ſin: Now we read that there was ſin before <hi>Moſes:</hi> this is proved, becauſe that death which is the wages of ſinne raigned from <hi>Adam</hi> to <hi>Moſes.</hi> If they maintaine free Election; they produce the decree gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven before the infants had none either good or evil. If they maintain that the Covenant of grace could not be diſanulled by the Law; they make it cleare that it did pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede the Law foure hundred and thirty yeares. If they publiſh that Chriſt is grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then the Angells; they prove it by his titles which were never conferred up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them. If they preach the weakneſſe of the
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:49144:75"/>Jewiſh prieſthood, they take it from this, that the Scripture hath ſubſtituted for it another, of anorder altogether different to it, after the order of <hi>Melchiſedech:</hi> for if per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fection had been in the Leviticall Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, what need had there been that ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the Prieſt ſhould ariſe, which was accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the order of <hi>Aron?</hi> If they teach that Jeſus Chriſt ought to die, they note, that where there is a Teſtament, there the death of the Teſtatour ought to intervene, before the heires can have benefit thereof. In brief if they ſpeak of the reſurrection, or of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther points of faith, their diſcourſe never conſiſts in bare aſſertions, but in reaſons, and demonſtrative proofs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="143" facs="tcp:49144:75" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>CHAP VII. <hi>Of Popular reaſons, as well in the Romane Religion, as amongſt the vulgar of the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox Churches. The difference betwixt the maximes of faith, and thoſe of charity.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THoſe which among the vulgar rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon upon matters of Religion, are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed to conceive them as reaſons one may call popular. Theſe reaſons are taken from the ſuperficies, not from the very ſubſtance of truth. This is the reaſon why oft times they are found falſe: although their facility render them plauſible to the ignorant. If it were needfull one might ſhew that the Romane Religion is for the moſt part propt up by popular reaſons. Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular is the compariſon of Interceſſours, which are employed towards the Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dees of this world, brought for the Invoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Saints. Popular is the queſtion whether we ought to condemn our anceſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, and ſo many ſouls, which hold the
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:49144:76"/>faith we at this day diſallow. Popular are the marks, under which they repreſent the Church: For the antiquity, multitude, locall ſucceſſion, are not eſſentiall proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties thereof. Popular are the auſterities, faſtings, ſcourgings, and externall mortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Monks profeſſion. Popular are the images and the title which is given them, that they are the booke of Ideots.</p>
               <p>The moſt ordinary reaſon which autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſeth the reaſon of the common people is that of charity. Prayers for the dead have been covered under this pretence; and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſometime have extended even to hell, praying even for the damned, not to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them wholly from pain (knowing that is impoſſible) but for to procure for them ſome diminution thereof: whereunto cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity carrieth them. The maximes of chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty are more perſuaſive, and efficacious a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the common people, then the maximes of faith. The reaſon thereof is, becauſe that thoſe of faith are more remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from the appearance, and have not ſo much relation with reaſon and naturall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:49144:76"/>as thoſe of charity, which are more intelligible, and more agreeing with the common notion of men. Notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſay truth, every act of Religion which is undertaken without faith, is alſo without charity. And the charity of the ignorant, is a ſtrange fire which is not acceptable at the altar.</p>
               <p>But our diſcourſe properly concerns them who being orthodox in points of Religion, prop not up the belief of them but upon popular reaſons, ſuch as are ſimilitudes and arguments of this kind. Thoſe which are found in Scripture are not of this rank, for the authority thereof makes them become demonſtrations, and undoubted proofs. But all others have no other vertue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to clear being beſides uncapable to prove; notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the vulgar will ſooner believe for one bare compariſon, which maketh no proof, then for a reaſon well concluding. This is it that ſimilitudes, particular exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and the like arguments have an appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance manifeſt to the ſenſe, and therefore move beyond eſſentiall reaſons, which are
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:49144:77"/>not perceiveable but by the underſtanding. Notwithſtanding this faith is not more ſolid. The man which conceives a point under the ſole reſemblance of truth, and not in the proper eſſence thereof, under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeth it not as he ought. This is to have a true opinion, but not a true knowledge. And more deceive themſelves by this meanes, preſuming they have the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of a point, inſtead whereof they have but the opinion. It ſufficeth not to ſay their opinion is conformable to the truth: For truth is not known by opinion. Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever deſires the knowledge thereof ought to endeavour the underſtanding rather of one concluding and formall reaſon, then ten thouſand Arguments which have but a bare reſemblance of truth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="147" facs="tcp:49144:77"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>Of whoſe who perſwade themſelves of the truth by falſe reaſons. Of thoſe which falſely accuſe themſelves.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT comes to paſſe that many believe a truth which is grounded on Scripture, but conceive it under a falſe reaſon. He believes the truth which holds we are ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by faith, and not by works. But if he believe that faith hath a prerogative, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is more excellent then works, this reaſon is falſe. For though faith be more excellent then works, the excellency there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is not the true cauſe why it juſtifies ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then works. All the vulgar ſpirits know how to maintain a truth in expreſſe tearmes of Scripture. But in that which the Scripture ſaith, they often imagine a reaſon either falſe or impertinent. So the friends of <hi>Job</hi> did maintaine Gods cauſe, his power, prudence, wiſdome, and juſtice: but by falſe preſuppoſition. And
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:49144:78"/>ſcarcely could one have ſaid that they err'd, if God himſelfe had not interpoſed his judgement in the diſpute. So ſome to exalt the grace of God, towards them, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe themſelves to be the greateſt ſinners in the world: imitating the Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul,</hi> who ſpeaketh of himſelf in this manner, although that <hi>Judas,</hi> and thoſe that had crucified the Prince of glory were (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt) more guilty. Now Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ranketh not himſelf ſimply amongſt the greateſt ſinners, but amongſt them which had not ſinn'd but through ignorance. 'Tis true that Originall ſin is equall naturally in all men, and 'tis the grace of God which reſtrains many therein. But that to am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plifie this grace, a man ſhould accuſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of actuall ſinnes which he never com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, this is a fooliſh ſort of falſhood. The water of ſprinkling which purified the unclean, did defile thoſe which were clean. If we would exalt the mercy of God, we have enow true arguments without ſearching imaginary for it. If we would ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtify his ſeverity, we find enow true crimes
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:49144:78"/>in our life, without impoſing falſe ones upon us. Whoſoever will ſpeak of God ought to ſpeak according unto God, that is to ſay, according to the truth, otherwiſe it is to ſpeak againſt God. To maintain truth with falſe reaſons, is to imitate the procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of <hi>Rebecca,</hi> who to the end the Oracle might be found true, had recourſe to an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſive means, uſing a fraudulent ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. There is nothing wherein one ought to be ſo circumſpect, as in ſpeaking for the truth. He that undertakes to maintain it, is ſubject to a grievous cenſure, if he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quits not himſelf thereof pertinently.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="150" facs="tcp:49144:79"/>
               <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>Of points whereof one ought to know the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. Many matters of Religion are ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous without their cauſes. The under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding whereof decides many queſtions. From whence come the greateſt part of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe matters of Religion are known principally either by their cauſes, or by their effects. The Deity, as being the higheſt cauſe of all, is not demonſtrable but by its ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects. Whoſe decrees ought alſo to be ſought rather in their effects, then in their cauſes. But the other points which are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate are repreſented to us with their cauſes: which teach us the true reaſons of every one of them. And in this the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned differ from the common people: For the vulgar ſees not the quality or truth of a point, but in the effects and ſtreames. But to comprehend it well, it behoves to ſee it in the ſpring.</p>
               <pb n="151" facs="tcp:49144:79"/>
               <p>Many matters of Religion are ridiculous without their cauſes. All the ceremoniall law, if one knows not the reaſons thereof, is nothing but a heap of unprofitable bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens: The Temple but a ſhambles, and the prieſthood but a vaine occupation. In lieu thereof conſidering them in their cauſes, every thing there is important even to the leaſt circumſtances. VVhoſoever ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that Jeſus Chriſt ſuffered out of the City of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> will admire the providence of this Law, which ordained that the ſacrifices of oblations, whereof the blood ought to be carried into the holy place, ſhould be conſumed out of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of the Camp, or of the City.</p>
               <p>We know that our Lord in the dayes of his fleſh, was environed with ſorrow and feare: But if we know not the cauſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, we make him inferiour to many mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs who bare a ſmiling face amidſt their puniſhments. The Jew underſtands no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in the Ceremoniall Lawes: for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he knowes the number thereof, all their particular forms, he is ignorant of the
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:49144:80"/>cauſe thereof, not knowing that they were given to ſerve onely till the coming of Chriſt. The true meanes to well under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand a point, is to learn the cauſes thereof; and the underſtanding of them is a ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign eye-ſalve to cleare ones ſelf of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny difficulties. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſheweth by the finall cauſe of the Law, that it is uncapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to juſtifie men: for (ſaith he) the Law came becauſe of tranſgreſſions, to wit to diſcover not to cover them. And indeed they which think to be juſtified by the works of the Law, know not why it was given. The Law was never given to juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.21. on the contrary its office is to condemne men.</p>
               <p>A great part of errours which waſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and likewiſe of them which trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble it at this day, proceeds from this, that the cauſe is taken for the effect, or the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect is taken for the cauſe. Inſtead that the Sabbath is made for man, Phariſaiſme concluded that man was made for the Sabbath. Inſtead that meats were not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean, but becauſe they were forbidden,
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:49144:80"/>ſuperſtition, believed them to be forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den becauſe they were uncleane. Inſtead than the alter ſanctified the offering they would by their Maximes, that the offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing did ſanctifie the alter. Inſtead that the Scripture ſanctifieth the Church, it is maintained that the Church, ſanctifieth the Scripture. Inſtead that juſtification produceth works, they hold that works produce juſtification. And 'tis likwiſe diſputed whether faith depend on election or election depend on faith. This turning topſie turvy is ordinary amongſt the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, who believe that the perſon is accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table for his works, inſtead that the works are acceptable for the perſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="154" facs="tcp:49144:81"/>
               <head>CHAP. X. <hi>Of the ignorance of the vulgar, who believe that one ought not to ſearch nor give any other reaſon of the points of Religion, then the will of God.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF twere not the will of God that we ſhould know why, and how he work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, we could not know how our Lord could be born of a Virgin, yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding this is one of the prime Articles of our faith. He hath not ſaid why inſtead of cauſing the <hi>Hebrews</hi> to paſſe when they came out of Egypt by the Philiſtines country, which was the ſtraight way to enter into <hi>Canaan,</hi> he led them by a great circuit full of wandrings and inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences. Nor why having given to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> the land of the <hi>Amorites,</hi> his poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ought not to have poſſeſſed it but at the end of 400 yeares, <hi>Gen.</hi> 15. Nor why the bill of divorce was permitted the Jewes. Nor why he diſapproved <hi>Davids</hi> deſigne
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:49144:81"/>touching the building of the Temple. And a thouſand other effects of his providence, whereof he would have us know the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</p>
               <p>Many think they know enough thereof, when they referre all things ſimply to the will of God, which they ſay ſufficeth for all reaſon: and that in every point, be it hiſtoricall, or dogmaticall, when one asks why it is ſo, one ought to content himſelf with ſaying that God would have it ſo, or hath ſo ordained. This Maxime teacheth ignorance under the ſhaddow of modeſty. By this meanes there's no queſtion but may be avoided in two words: and the verieſt idiot ſhall be capable to give a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution thereof. 'Tis true the will of God is the ſoveraigne cauſe of all things, and the onely reaſon of a great part thereof. But this anſwer ſuffiſeth not for all queſtions, nay in many matters it is impertinent. When one asketh how <hi>Abraham</hi> was ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified, this would be an abſurdity to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer that he was juſtified by the will of God, inſtead of ſaying it was by faith. An
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:49144:82"/>abſurdity to ſhew the firſt cauſe when the ſecond is demanded. An abſurdity to produce the will of God, when the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion is of the formall or inſtrumentall cauſe. An abſurdity to name the Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect inſtead of the matter. This is to anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hilate the diſpenſation which God hath eſtabliſhed in his works, and to breake downe thoſe ſteps by which he would have us climb up unto him. To think to leape over all at one leape, is extreme folly. A man that alledgeth nothing but the will of God upon a Subject propoſed, under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands not what this will of God is. For to underſtand it, 'tis neceſſary to know wherein it conſiſteth, and how it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns the matter in queſtion. Now the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of this point preſuppoſeth the knowledge of ſecond cauſes, by which the will of God worketh. He that alleadgeth the ſecond cauſes, and gives reaſons there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, alleadgeth the will of God: For God hath willed that ſuch things ſhould be ſo for ſuch reaſons, and theſe reaſons are one part of his will. When the Diſciples
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:49144:82"/>asked why they could not deliver the man poſſeſſed, the vulgar anſwer would import, becauſe it pleaſed not God. But our Lord notes their incredulity, as a cauſe of this inability, and ſhewes faſting and prayer as the meanes neceſſary to the expulſion of the Devill. When Saint <hi>Paul</hi> was buffet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Sathan he did not ſimply underſtand that ſuch was the will of God: but that his power was accompliſhed in weakneſſe.</p>
               <p>When we ſearch the cauſes of our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, This would be a dangerous pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding to deſire to mount up to Election without paſſing by the middle meanes. The will of God is the firſt reaſon, but the laſt anſwer one ought to give to a que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="158" facs="tcp:49144:83"/>
               <head>CHAP XI. <hi>Objections of the vulgar touching the reaſons Scripture expreſſeth not, and how we may know them.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Scripture is full of Lawes and myſteries, whereof we know not the reaſons. We read of divers ceremonies, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers points of hiſtory and doctrine, the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular reaſons whereof are not yet found out. But oft times we abuſe our ſelves, by believing that the Scripture diſcovers not the reaſon thereof, under colour that our ignorance hindreth us from ſeeing them. This is a common objection in the mouth of the vulgar, when they heare men reaſon upon any matter, to alleadge that this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is not at all expreſt in Scripture. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly the Scripture expreſſeth not why the Law permitted Homicides confin'd within the Cities of Refuge, to return to their houſes after the death of the high Prieſt. And notwithſtanding, beſides po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litick
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:49144:83" rendition="simple:additions"/>reaſons which may be given for this Law, It is impudence to deny that it meant to repreſent the efficacy of Chriſts death. But to produce an example more formall to this purpoſe, the reaſon for which our Lord was put in a new ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchre, wherein never any one was buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, is notwithſtanding leſſe expreſt: Yet notwithſtanding we ſay that the wiſdome of God would prevent the malice of the Jews, who not able to deny the truth of his reſurrection, might have diſputed the cauſe thereof, pretending that he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered life by touching the bones of ſome Prophet, as he that was raiſed in the grave of <hi>Eliſha.</hi> This reaſon is not grounded but upon conjecture, but of ſo great appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, that it were a ſhame to reject it. In many things the very effect ſhews its cauſe If any man ask why Jeſus Chriſt truſted <hi>Judas</hi> with the bag, whoſe covetouſnes he knew, rather then another of his diſciples; the reaſon thereof is evident to him that conſiders that the convenience of this of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice rendered his treaſon ſo much the more
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:49144:84"/>inexcuſable. VVhen the Scripture tells not at all why God permitted ſinne, why he would harden <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> why he ſuffers the veſſells of wrath; the effects which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed thence, ſhew that ſin is the cauſe thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XII. <hi>Of the prudence that is requiſite in the exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of points where the cauſe is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine Of a Ly. Whether Satan made</hi> Pilates <hi>wife ſpeak for the innocence of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT is true that one ought carefully to take heed of thoſe cauſes, and reaſons which are not plain unto us, but by a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecturall appearance: for the conſequences thereof may be fooliſh and dangerous. Some have thought that <hi>Jacob</hi> in all the proceedings he made to gaine his fathers bleſſing, was inſpired by the ſpirit of God; But the conſequence thereof ſounds very
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:49144:84"/>ill. For then it muſt be, that the Holy Ghoſt had dictated the deceitfull words which came from <hi>Jacobs</hi> mouth. Now God is an enemy of lies. He may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to kill, but not to pronounce a falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood: although a barely be not ſo bad as manſlaughter. The reaſon thereof is, that man ſlaughter may be ſometimes an act of Juſtice; but a ly can never be truth. And therefore God himſelf may kill, but he can never ly. On the other ſide many have believed, that the dreame which came to <hi>Pilates</hi> wife, proceeded from Satan, who foreſeeing his own ruine in the death of Chriſt, aſſaied to hinder the ſentence. If ſpeculations might be received, I could ſay that Satan might be in doubt of the quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Jeſus Chriſt, ſeing in him ſo great wonders as conſtrained them to call him the ſon of God, and then againe an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame annihilation which ſeemed incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patible with his divinity: ſo that he thought to overwhelm him with torments, as he got his deſire on the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> by flatteries. That although he knew that
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:49144:85"/>the future death of Chriſt was foretold by the Prophets, by the ſacrifices and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther figures, and by the faith of the ancient fathers: notwithſtanding he might ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, that as <hi>Iſaac</hi> upon the point he was to be ſacrifiſed by the expreſſe command of God, was exempted from death, ſome ſuch like thing might befall Jeſus Chriſt. I might alſo ſay, that Satan having the day before procured the death of Chriſt, and employed <hi>Judas</hi> to this purpoſe, it is very incredible that he changed his mind in ſo ſhort a time. But to come nearer unto the buſineſſe, this dreame which happened to <hi>Pilates</hi> wife is inſerted in the hiſtory as proceeding from an extraordinary cauſe. If this cauſe be uncertain, yet 'tis dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to attribute to the power of, Satan, that which might proceed from the inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of God. By the ſame reaſon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore alleadged we may conclude, that <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late</hi> as well as his wife, was induced by Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan to pronounce Chriſt innocent. But certainly I had rather take the Teſtimony of his innocence, for the voice of God then for a ſubtilty of the Devil.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="163" facs="tcp:49144:85"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIII. <hi>Of hidden reaſons of ſome impertinent opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons on this ſubject.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>According to the vulgar, all publick ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities, or particular, are but pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments of ſinne, or corrections, or tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alls. But they ought to be referred to many other cauſes which are to us unknown. VVe ſee not the providence of God but in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells. If we could ſee his works in their to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, and join all ages together, we might perceive in their linking together an order of cauſes, and juſtice, which cannot be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in retaile. Some hold that the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall ſins of the fathers are not puniſhed in their children, unleſſe when they are made partakers thereof with them; And notwithſtanding many children, never having committed any evill, have been borne with notable infirmities, which their fathers ſinnes have drawn upon them. The piety of <hi>Joſias</hi> hindred not that
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:49144:86"/>God ſhould viſit in his own perſon, the i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrie of <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> although with ſuch a temper as turned this puniſhment into mercy. In the contentions of theſe times, touching Gods foreknowledge, reproba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſuch like points, every man at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts to produce ſuch an opinion that God may be found juſt. To this purpoſe all the diſtinctions, and reaſons are ſought out, which may be conceived. But if God himſelf ſhould heare out of the midſt of a whirlwind; that man which thinks he well pleadeth the cauſe of God, will be found to have maintianed it with bad ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments; And without doubt, we ſhall heare of reaſons whereof man never thought upon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="165" facs="tcp:49144:86"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIIII. <hi>Of points reſulting from others, and of the multitude of conſequences.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THere is nothing wherein the vulgar is more ſubject to fail, then in the dedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of conſequences, when one point is drawn from another. This is prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally ſeen when one comes from a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>all point to a particular: for generall Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mes are eaſie to the common people; But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rant of knowing their exceptions, they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re eaſily deceived, when they will apply <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hem to ſome particular ſubject. The ſame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ncongruity is often found, when they make a generall rule of a particular exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le. It is true that in ſome matters, an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mple alone is ſufficient to make up an u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſall propoſition; if we could produce onely one man which hath been juſtified <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r ſaved by works, it would univerſally f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow that the juſtification of all others
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:49144:87"/>ought to be attributed to works: The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whereof is evident; ſuch as is the juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of one, ſuch is the juſtification of all others. On the other ſide, if we ſhew but one which was juſtified without works; this is an univerſall Maxime for all. And the onely example of <hi>Abraham</hi> produced by Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> is as ſtrong as a demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: but one cannot make a Maxime of this that <hi>David</hi> never ſaw the children of the righteous brought to beggerie. The po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy which God ſet up in <hi>Iſraell,</hi> impeded this calamity, whereunto many ſuch as <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus</hi> might be ſubject. <hi>Deut.</hi> 15.4. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37. and 25.</p>
               <p>Many think they do enough, when they draw a conſequence from a principle, and then another, and finally an entire chain of concluſions; but the more a conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence is removed from its principle the more feeble and weak it is. Thoſe which are immediately tyed to their foundation, are ſtrongeſt: as in a building, the part which is neareſt to the foundation, is alſo the firmeſt. Others, in what proportion
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:49144:87"/>they are removed therefrom, loſe their force, and the laſt often ends in points, and ſpiders webbes, more ſubtile then ſolid.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="section">
            <head>The fourth Section.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>Generall conſiderations on the Scripture. Of matters which ſeem vulgar and of eaſie underſtanding.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>GOD would not that the Scripture ſhould be very ſhort, to the end we might abound in knowledge; nor over large, that our time might ſuffice to learn it. There was a King that read it fourty times. Method is requiſite thereunto. They who read it onely in retail, and in confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, cannot comprehend the harmony and contexture thereof.</p>
               <p>The vulgar ought to know that the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:49144:88"/>thereof into Chapters and verſes, having been made by godly men, but ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to erre, is found oftentimes irregular, ſeparating that which ought to follow in a continued threed, and confounding that which ought to be diſtinguiſhed. As for the reſt, 'tis true that no man can promiſe himſelf a perfect underſtanding thereof. There are more then a thouſand paſſages which no man ever yet underſtood. The Argument of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> concerning thoſe which are baptiſed for the dead; the fire which muſt prove every mans work; the Priſon wherein S. <hi>Peter</hi> lodgeth the ſpirits of all men; the thouſand yeares of the Revelations, from whence the Millenaries have taken their names; are to us as ſealed letters, nor to ſpeak of an infinite number of queſtions in hiſtory, in Chronologie, in the names of places, plants, precious ſtones, inſtruments of muſick, and other ſubjects, the knowledge whereof is reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for heaven. But on the other ſide the cleareſt paſſages are oft times made ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure by prejudices, which cover as a veile
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:49144:88"/>the eyes of many readers. The true cauſe which renders the Scripture dark to them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s this, becauſe they ſearch that which is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot there. We will repreſent ſomething upon this point.</p>
               <p>Many matters of Scripture ſeem triviall. It ſaith, that the ſun ſhines as well on the on juſt, as the juſt; that we brought nothing into the world, &amp; ſhal carry nothing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from: a thing which experience ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly teacheth. That concord is good amongſt brethren; that we ought to render to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one what belongs unto him; that we ought not to do to others what we would not have done to us; and the like propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which the law of nature teacheth the moſt barbarous; that he that is invited to a feaſt, chooſe not the higheſt place; that he which ought, ſhould agree with his Creditor, to ſhun the Priſon; And other inſtructions of prudence, of well being, and adminiſtration which every man knows without Scripture. God gave a commiſſion to the Prophet to publiſh an Oracle, the tenour whereof was, that all
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:49144:89"/>fleſh is as graſſe, and the glory thereof as graſſe: which ſeemes to be ſufficiently known of it ſelf, without extraordinary revelation. The 49. <hi>Pſal.</hi> calls all the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the earth to heare things rare and excellent, which it promiſeth to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver unto them; the ſumme whereof is this, <hi>that every man is mortall, that the wiſe man dyeth as well as the fool, that riches exempts no man from the grave;</hi> and other ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which the verieſt ideots ſufficiently know, though they never had been written: from hence it cometh that the ignorant ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mireth not the Scripture, becauſe they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it tells them nothing new; and in truth if the words thereof contained nothing but what appeares manifeſt, theſe matters would be purely vulgar: But this is that which deceives the greateſt part of readers, or rather their ignorance deceives them, in that they think theſe propoſitions of ſcripture have no other ſenſe, then that which is common and naturall to the groſſeſt perſons. Theſe are, as for the terms, the ſame ſentences which are dictated un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:49144:89"/>us either by nature, or by reaſon, or by experience, or by the univerſall voice of mankind: But the ſence which they have in ſcripture, reacheth much further. That which ſeemes there to be triviall is full of rarities, which are not perceivable to all ſorts of ſpirits. If there be queſtion of a paſſage which ſpeaks of death, the world is full of preachers which will give a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription thereof, which will declaim in a pathetick manner, and will ſay all that which the ſimple know well enough: But this is but to touch the ſuperficies of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Sometimes it pronounceth proverbs taken from the mouth of common people, nay of Pagan authors; but it heightneth the ſence thereof, and referres to an end farre more noble. Many Philoſophers might have conceived the ſame morall precepts, nay in the ſame tearmes with ſcrcipture, but not to animate them with a ſence ſo high, and ſo compleat. This is the admirable art of the Holy Ghoſt, to hide the rareſt myſteries under the appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the moſt common matters. VVe
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:49144:90"/>reſerve the examples hereof to another diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</p>
               <p>The ignorant who believe that all the ſubſtance of a paſſage conſiſts in that which is therein vulgar, the underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whereof is eaſie, imagine they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it very well, and think they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend all the ſenſe thereof. The opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion they have of this eaſineſſe abuſeth them. VVhen one finds a paſſage which ſeems ſo eaſie, one may aſſure himſelf, that there is ſome notable difficulty in it. Thoſe which ſeem moſt clear, are very often moſt obſcure. If there be any thing which ſeems to be clear and intelligible, ſuch are ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militudes taken from common and ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble things, as of a ſower; of a net caſt into the ſea; of agrain of muſtard-ſeed; of leaven put in meal, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Thoſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pariſons becauſe they are familiar are even contemptible to the verieſt ideors; and there is none of them which attributes not to himſelf the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding thereof; notwithſtanding, it may be there are ſew men that comprehend the full ſenſe thereof: not to ſpeak in the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:49144:90"/>of the Potter, that of the wild o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live uſed by Saint <hi>Paul</hi> upon the ſubject of the calling of the Gentiles, hath divers branches marvelouſly high, whereunto all cannot attain.</p>
               <p>One may referre hither divers ſubjects which ſeem to be within the cogniſance of humane arts and ſciences, As the <hi>Pleia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des</hi> and other Celeſtiall ſignes mentioned in <hi>Job,</hi> for Aſtrologie. The remedie appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the Carbuncle of <hi>Ezekiah,</hi> and the third day obſerved for the moſt pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, in the wound of the <hi>Sichemites,</hi> for Phyſick. The ſtatue of <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> for buriall. The temple, and royall houſes of <hi>Solomon,</hi> for Architecture; &amp; an infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of points which belong to Naturall Philoſophy. In effect there's no doubt but the Scripture contains in it many admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſecrets of this quality: but this is but the bark of a marrow more ſubſtantiall and wholſome.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="174" facs="tcp:49144:91"/>
               <head>CHAP. 2. <hi>Of matters which ſeeme unprofitable in Scripture. Conſiderations upon Chronolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, upon the Genealogies, Proper names, Ceremoniall Laws, Rules, Particularities little conſiderable in appearance, and hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories of enormous Acts.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TO underſtand the Scripture 'tis not enough to know what it ſaith; 'Tis neceſſary alſo to know why it ſaith it. For the diſcourſe thereof tends oftentimes to abut the words expreſſe not. There is nothing ſo cleare as the Morall law; the precepts thereof are evident; there is no man ſo brutiſh, which underſtands not very well when it ſpeaks of honouring fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and mother, of abſteining from homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide, from falſe witneſſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, this law was co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered with a veil, and that the Jews could not ſee <hi>Moſes</hi> face. They did comprehend well the ſenſe thereof; but ſaw not the aim
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:49144:91"/>thereof, which ſeemed to contradict eve the language and the appearance of it. For the law promiſed life to him that fulfilled it; and yet notwithſtanding this was not the intention of the Law to induce us to ſearch for life by the fulfilling therof. Our Lord ſaid, <hi>If thou wilt enter into life, keep the commandements:</hi> and notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this propoſition tended to an end quite different, to wit that we ſhould not hope for ſalvation by obſervation of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements. The ſame ought to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in divers other paſſages.</p>
               <p>The Scripture is full of an infinity of matters, which conſidered in themſelves, ſeem to be wholly unprofitable, or at leaſt of very little importance, if one take not heed at what they aim at. It is true that ſome are either more profitable, or more conſiderable then others; our Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf diſtinguiſheth the greater commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from the leſſer. Without doubt the hiſtory of Chriſts paſſion is more neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry then that of <hi>Sampſon,</hi> or the victories of <hi>David,</hi> or the deſcription of <hi>Solomons</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace.
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:49144:92"/>If it be ſo that the Scripture contains nothing ſuperfluous, there is neither a tache, nor a goats haire in all the Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, which ſerves not to the perfection of it.</p>
               <p>To this purpoſe are the accounts of the yeares, which the Scriptures obſerve ſo punctually. It were a very great brutiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to be ignorant, whether the world harh continued a long time, and how. The dayes of the ancient Fathers, and the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the following ages, which the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hiſtory calculates ſo exactly, give us their chronology. The 430 years which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pired the very night the Hebrews came out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> publiſhed the immutable truth of God, whoſe promiſe failed not to be ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected at the named day. The thirtieth year of Jeſus Chriſt, wherein he began to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe the Office of a redeemer, was the age in which the Prieſts entred into their charge. The periods which are obſerved from the creation to the floud, from the floud to the promiſe, from the promiſe to the Law, from the Law, to the building of the Temple, from thence to the captivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:49144:92"/>and from the captivity to Chriſt; their extent, their number, their relation and proportion are all full of wonders. Seven yeares were imployed to the conqueſt of <hi>Canaan,</hi> Seven yeares to build the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſeventie yeares it was in raiſing, ſeven times ſeven yeares they were hindred from rebuilding it, and ſeven times ſeventy years in the whole, (which are the weekes of <hi>Daniel</hi>) it ſtood till the ſecond deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; which happened the tenth of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt,</hi> which was the very day wherein it had been ruined the firſt time, more then five hundred fifty years before. The life of <hi>Moſes</hi> is found equally divided into three, forty yeares he was a Courtier in <hi>Egypt;</hi> forty yeares a ſhepherd in <hi>Madian;</hi> forty yeares a conducter of the people in the wilderneſſe.</p>
               <p>The ſame harmony we obſerve in times, is ſeen in generations. <hi>Moſes</hi> the Lawgiver, was the ſeventh man after <hi>Abraham,</hi> to whom God gave the promiſes; <hi>Abraham</hi> the ſeventh from <hi>Heber,</hi> of whom the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews are deſcended; <hi>Heber</hi> the ſeventh
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:49144:93"/>from <hi>Enoch,</hi> the firſt that was caught up to heaven; <hi>Enoch</hi> the ſeventh from <hi>Adam.</hi> Ten generations from the Creation to the flood; ten generations from the flood to the promiſe. From <hi>Abraham</hi> to <hi>David</hi> fourteen generations, from <hi>David</hi> to the captivity fourteen generations, from the captivity to Chriſt fourteen generations, which make in all, forty two, and anſwer the forty two journeys of the Iſraelites, from their departure from <hi>Egypt</hi> to the land of <hi>Canaan.</hi> But moreover, theſe Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nealogies ſerve to ſhew us, beſides the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall of every nation, that which brought forth to us the Son of God; for it was a matter of importance that his people, his tribe, and his familie, whereof he was to be born, ſhould be exactly marked out. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto ſerves the catalogue of ſo many per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, the number whereof is found in Scripture.</p>
               <p>But beſides this liſt of names in Genea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logies, we read there are an infiniteneſſe of others, the knowledge whereof ſeems not to be of great fruit; yet notwitſtanding
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:49144:93"/>we can ſhew their importance in divers examples. It ſufficieth me to note by the by, that which may be without much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, how we ought to underſtand the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſall of our Lord, touching <hi>Lazarus,</hi> and the wicked rich man, to wit, whether in tearmes of hiſtory, or in form of a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable; whether it may be thought that <hi>Lazarus</hi> by changing of the dialect, is the proper name of <hi>Eleazar</hi> the ſervant of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham.</hi> Thus Jeſus Chriſt placeth <hi>Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> in the boſome, or at the table of this Patriarch, whoſe houſhold ſervant he had been. It may be there is a ſecret <hi>Antithe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis</hi> between the quality of this wicked rich man, who is repreſented, as being of the blood of <hi>Abraham,</hi> whoſe ſon he is called, and that quality of the other who was but a ſervant. That Maxim which imports that every narration wherein is expreſt the proper name of ſome one, ought to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for hiſtorie, is not alwayes to be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
               <p>I will not ſtay long to ſhew what uſe there is at this day of the Ceremoniall
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:49144:94"/>Lawes of the Old Teſtament. This ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject requires a longer diſcourſe, I will only ſay that this is one of the richeſt cabbinets of Divinity, full of ineſtimable Jewells; but one ought to be very expert, to know the kinds, the properties, the uſe, and the value of every one of them. Jeſus Chriſt is there painted out unto us, in divers ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, which ſerve us to convince the blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Jews. The numbring up of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers ſins, for which this Law ordained ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, is an aſſurace to them that are guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty thereof, that they may obtain pardon. Such a one as being faln into perjury, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves he hath committed a ſin which the Scripture pronounceth unpardonable, hath found a remedie againſt deſpaire, hearing the Ceremoniall Law, which preſcribes a ſinne Offering altogether expreſſe in favor of wilfull perjury, which it would not do, were this crime unpardonable.</p>
               <p>We find alſo in the Old Teſtament many rules, and narrations, which ſerve in ſhew, neither for faith, nor manners, nor for our comfort. This is ſeen princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:49144:94"/>in the books of <hi>Moſes,</hi> that the moſt important matters are touched but in few words, And on the contrary, divers mean things, and leſſe conſiderable, are there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented at length. The redemption by the Meſſias which God promiſed Man, immediately after his fall; the calling of the Gentiles foretold to <hi>Abraham;</hi> the Prieſthood of <hi>Melchiſedech,</hi> the moſt il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious figure of Chriſt; and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther points of ſoveraigne doctrine, are ſet downe there but very briefly. Whereas the birth of <hi>Iſmael,</hi> the contract of <hi>Iſaacs</hi> marriage, and the like hiſtories, are there delivered largely, even to the ſmalleſt par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars. I give hereof this reaſon, that the Church being in the age of infancy her inſtruction ought to conſiſt more in rudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, then in high and hard leſſons, for ſhe was not then capable thereof. But it may be demanded what uſe may be made by reading them at this day? It is all full of myſteries. The onely hiſtorie of <hi>Agar</hi> and <hi>Iſmael,</hi> interpreted by Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> even to the meaneſt circumſtances, ſhews what we
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:49144:95" rendition="simple:additions"/>may judge of all other hiſtories of the Old Teſtament, although we ſee not what they aim at. God would teach us great things by ſmall. Divers particulars of ſmall conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, which the Scriptures declare very largely, ſerve to make us ſee how many ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable effects have proceeded from frivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous occaſions: witneſſe <hi>Jacobs</hi> primogeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. The law forbidding to <hi>take the old,</hi> &amp; the <hi>young</hi> birds, to wit in their neſts, <hi>to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muzle the ox that treades out the corn,</hi> &amp; the like lawes extend further then they ſeem. The New Teſtament mentions the <hi>parch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi> and <hi>cloak</hi> of Saint <hi>Paul;</hi> the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell he gives <hi>Timothy, to uſe a little wine for the weakneſſe of his ſtomack;</hi> the bury<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the wicked rich man, where that of <hi>Lazarus</hi> is omitted; and in divers hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries many circumſtances which the vulgar hold to be unprofitable for want of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their cauſes. The act of Jeſus Chriſt ſtretching forth the hand to touch the leper appeared not conſiderable but to them who knew the Law by which this touching was declared a defilement. The ſame Law
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:49144:95" rendition="simple:additions"/>forbad the high Prieſt, who repreſented Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, to enter into any houſe wherein <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>here was any dead: yet notwithſtanding our Lord himſelf touched the bier, nay the dead body, to wit the daughter of <hi>Jairus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>VVe may find in theſe particulars an incomparable richneſſe of doctrine.</p>
               <p>'Tis not enough to know the generall intention of a paſſage; each of them hath a particular end. There is one meaning of the burning buſh, another of the living crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures painted out in the viſion of <hi>Ezekiel.</hi> The Pſalmiſt ſpeaking of the food which God provides for beaſts, makes mention of young ravens, rather then of other fouls of the aire, for a ſpeciall reaſon. The Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on repreſents not Chriſt to all the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, under the ſame figure. To one it ſhews the ſtars, and the golden Candleſticks; to another, it makes it ſee the two edged ſword; to another flaming eyes, and the feet as of braſſe. His titles are divers ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the diverſity of ſubjects. Many know in generall, that the ceremonies fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure out Chriſt, but know not how, and
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:49144:96" rendition="simple:additions"/>in what quality each of them repreſent him. There is none of them which hath not, beſides the generall intention of the Law, their particular aime and reaſon, for want of underſtanding them diſtinctly, makes the reading of them contemptible, and envied by the common people.</p>
               <p>Many alſo not knowing at what the Scripture aimes, are aſtoniſhed at the reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal of divers enormous things which it par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulariſeth ſo carefully. I put not in this rank thoſe which are ſymbolical; as the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement made to <hi>Hoſea,</hi> that he ſhould get unto him a whore, this is but a parable. But the inceſt of <hi>Judas</hi> with his ſons wife ſeems fitter to have been buried with him, then to be inſerted in the holy hiſtory, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven with ſo many ſhamefull and horrid circumſtances: yet notwithſtanding if one heed the arrogance of the Jews, which inſolently glory of their extraction, who ground even their election and divine alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance on the vertues of their Patriarks; One ſhall find this error cannot be better refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, nor this pride better taken down, then
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:49144:96"/>by making them ſee the proceedings of their father, guilty of a thouſand filthy acts.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>Of the method which ſeems defective in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny diſcourſes of Scripture. Of the ſtile thereof. Of ſuperfluous words. Of ſtrange ſimilitudes. Of the imitation of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture language. Of myſterious omiſſions.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THere are found many diſcourſes in the Scripture which ſeem to be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out order, and without connexion, built with pieces ill joyned, nay (in the judgement of the ignorant) extravagant, and from the purpoſe.</p>
               <p>The Lamentations of <hi>Jeremy,</hi> a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Pſalmes, divers Sermons of our Lord, ſome Epiſtles of the Apoſtles, keep not in appearance any regular method. Many ſubjects ſeem ranked confuſedly in
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:49144:97"/>hiſtory, unleſſe one ſee their ſubjects, the connection, and their aim, as in the Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy of Saint <hi>Stephen,</hi> and other places. One may take notice of cenſures made as it ſeemeth out of ſeaſon, nay, which is more, divers anſwers which concern not the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and in no wayes touch the queſtion propoſed. The vulgar interpreters are much troubled when they muſt expound ſuch paſſages, and ſhew themſelves ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous, endeavouring to reduce them to the ordinary rules of their Logick: By this meanes they give them a contrary and forced ſenſe. What may be ſaid upon this ſubject cannot be comprehended in this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridgement: I will touch but one point thereof for example of all the reſt.</p>
               <p>Sometimes it is ſaid in the Goſpell, that Jeſus anſwered, where notwithſtanding it appeareth not by any circumſtance of Scripture that any had ſpoke unto him. Some are aſtoniſhed then, why it is ſaid he anſwered, when none had asked him. I take this tearm not for a bare Hebraiſme, but indeed for a propoſall relative to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:49144:97"/>Now many which opened not their mouth in the preſence of Jeſus Chriſt, cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed not to ſpeake in the ſecret of their heart, but their thoughts being known to him, he anſwered the ſubject of their thoughts.</p>
               <p>We ought alſo to obſerve, that where the Scripture oft-times breaks off that which ſeems ſhould have followed, in the thred of the ſame diſcourſe, and inſerts a ſubject quite different, whereof the hearers never thought; If the conſtruction thereof be not alwaies Grammaticall, it is reall; conſiſting more in the coherence of my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries then in the forme of words.</p>
               <p>In that which the Scripture ſaith one ought even to conſider why it ſpeaks in ſuch tearms; for when it expreſſeth the ſame thing by divers names, this diverſitie of words repreſenteth alwaies ſome diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie of qualitie in the ſame ſubject. Such a thing is called by one name in one paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, which is otherwiſe named in another, and this for a notable cauſe. <hi>Moſes</hi> (<hi>Exod.</hi> 3.) asked what was the name of God, that
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:49144:98"/>is to ſay, in what qualitie he ſhould ſpeak; whether as <hi>Elohim,</hi> or as <hi>Jehovah,</hi> or as <hi>Shadai,</hi> or <hi>Adma,</hi> or according to ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther name by which he is called. It is to be noted, that the title of <hi>Jehovah,</hi> which is tranſlated <hi>Lord,</hi> was not given him in all the Scripture touching the Creation, but onely after the making of man. In one place the Scripture ſaith, that Jeſus Chriſt ſitteth on the right hand of God; In ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that he ſtandeth at the right hand of God. I have before ſpoken of the redun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants which ſeeme to be in Scripture. When it ſaith that ſuch a man lived ſo many years, and then died; Theſe two laſt words ſeeme to be ſuperfluous, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine notwithſtanding a ſubſtantiall addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. It gives this Epitaph but to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchs which lived before the flood; Of all thoſe which died after <hi>Noah,</hi> it ſaith barely, ſuch a man lived ſo many yeares, without adding that he died; Which thing is conſiderable. It is to be obſerved alſo, whether the Scripture it ſelfe ſpeaks, or whether ſome body els ſpeake in it. The
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:49144:98"/>ſimilitude which compares God to a man that was dead aſleep with too much drink, is but an echo, or an Ironicall repetition of the idolaters language, who ſpake of God in thoſe jolly tearmes. It is to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted alſo, that the Scripture ſometime ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth a thing by its contrary; As when one is accuſed to have bleſſed God, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>note the moſt horrible impiety that may be; Theſe obſervations require many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, which we omit.</p>
               <p>I will ſpeake onely one word of a queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that may be made, to wit, whether wee may not accuſtome our ſelves to write, and ſpeak the ſame ſtyle with the Scripture. There are found ſome that affect its lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, and aſſay to counterfeit its voyce to authorize their dreams, and make them paſſe for Oracles; But they are barbariſms in divinitie have made thoſe dreames be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted for ſtrange. It were therefore to be wiſhed, that thoſe that ſpeak according to the truth of Scripture, had alſo the phraſe, and language thereof. A Sermon woven not with ſuperfluous, or imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:49144:99"/>quotations, but with tearms, and ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of the Holy Ghoſt, joyned, and ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in their proper places, nips off the lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtre of the moſt eloquent pieces. A colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction which might be made upon all ſorts of ſubjects, continuall reading, a method fit for this purpoſe, are a memorie ready, and preſent to occurrences, a judicious ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and long experience might frame the habit thereof. But we muſt obſerve, that as the Scripture often hides an extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie ſenſe under a common phraſe, wee may well have the ſame words of it, though not alwaies in ſo lofty a ſence. There is for example, ſometimes a reproofe, or a do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, al whoſe words imply ſome prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie which concernes not at all the preſent time, or any prediction whereof the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment is to us unknown. We may truly pronounce the ſame words as the Scripture, but in our mouth they are not Propheticall.</p>
               <p>To cloſe this Chapter, wee are not onely to conſider what the Scripture ſaith, but alſo very often why it conceales certaine
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:49144:99"/>things, for in many places it ſpeaketh e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by ſilence; and its ſilence is ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive. That which I would ſay concernes not thoſe matters whereupon the leaſt curious may raiſe queſtions, as upon the day of Chriſts Nativity; his actions from his infancy to his twelfth yeare, and from that time to his age of thirty yeares; and other points whereof the holy hiſtory ſpeakes not. It may bee diſputed alſo why the tribe of <hi>Dan</hi> is omitted. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel.</hi> 7. in a Catalogue where all others are ſo expreſly named. But the ſole omiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of <hi>Melchiſedechs</hi> Genealogie, of his birth, and death, ſhew that the very ſilence of Scripture is myſterious, including the image of Chriſts eternity. I doubt not but it containes many other examples of this kind, though our eye cannot ſee them all.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="192" facs="tcp:49144:100"/>
               <head>CHAP. IIII. <hi>Of infuſed knowledge. Of Apoſtleſhip. Of thoſe that know nothing but by books.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Lay aſide the queſtion whether the gifts of prophecie have wholly ceaſed. We call a Prophet not him which fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tells what is to come, as the vulgar under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, but him which hath graces extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily infuſed, for the underſtanding, and interpretation of the divine myſteries. Theſe lights are not given at this day in ſo eminent a degree as heretofore; but it may bee they are not wholly extinguiſhed, though they are rare, and communicated to very few perſons. Tis not enough to object, that there may be found ſome ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime divine, whoſe knowledge proceeds not from ſtudy, ſo much as other mens. The heavenly influences may deſcend as well into a library, as into a wilderneſſe; <hi>Daniel</hi> ſtudied on <hi>Jeremy</hi> when the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell came to ſpeake unto him. St. <hi>Paul</hi> amidſt the ordinary inſpirations of Gods
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:49144:100"/>ſpirit, even after he had bin in the third heaven, deſired that <hi>Timothy</hi> ſhould ſend him the books. Tis true when a man at this day hath ſo much ſpirituall wiſdome, as the chiefe Apoſtles, if he hath nor the ſame authority, nor the Prerogatives which were to them perſonall, and cannot be tranſmitted by any title of ſucceſſion. No man can be qualified as an Apoſtle, unleſſe he had ſeene Jeſus Chriſt raiſed from the dead, to the end he might ſpeake as an eye witneſſe. This ſerved as a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to St. <hi>Pauls</hi> enemies, to diſpure his Apoſtleſhip, alleadging that he being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted only after the aſcenſion of our Lord, he could not have ſeene him. But he had ſeen him in heaven; and in this very thing he had a very great advantage above the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Apoſtles, which ſaw him not but upon the earth. To come to our mark; although that divine knowledge is no more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated but by ordinary meanes, and above all, by the reading of divers au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours, I cannot hold them for great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, whoſe knowledge conſiſts but in a
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:49144:101"/>bare remembrance of what they have read. Much reading, and a good memory make not a knowing man. They that cannot ſay but what they have read have not the true gift of Prophecie; yet leſſe, thoſe poore ignorants which learne by heart o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other mens Sermons. Such ſhoulders are not capable to beare the arke of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Of eloquence. The principall part thereof is unknowne by the greateſt part of Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers. Of vulgar matters in Sermons. The excuſe and deceit of ignorant Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers. Whether the word of God be in like luſtre in the mouthes of all.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe firſt, and principall quality re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in a Biſhop, is to be didactick, to bee capable to teach excellent matters, and to handle them powerfully, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly. I ſtand not on them who under colour of the ſimplicity of the Scripture condemne abſolutely the uſe of eloquence
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:49144:101"/>in the interpretation thereof. Certainly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n effeminate diſcourſe woven with flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs, variagated with colours, and wantonly a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orned, is ſutable to the vulgar, as a pop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et to little children, is incompetible with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e Majeſty of the Goſpel. But a maſculine, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd vigorous eloquence cloathed with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>umptuous ornaments, and alwayes more naturall then artificiall, is not onely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enient but alſo neceſſary for a Miniſter. Nay hee is unworthy to ſpeake in the Church, which cannot ſpeake eloquent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y. They that are herein defective, are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſtomed to blame in an other that which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hey themſelves ſee doth well. For there is no man ſobrutiſh who deſires not, when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſpeakes in publique, to expreſſe himſelf in the beſt tearmes hee can. Furthermore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he vulgar give oftentimes the reputation of eloquence to many which have not the very ſhadow of it. So a man heapes toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether abundance of words, with a fine ſtile, though he hath not any true Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke, he ſhall paſſe in the eſteeme of the ignorant for a great Oratour. But that
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:49144:102"/>which is more conſiderable, the principall piece of eloquence conſiſteth not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures, and other ornaments of language; It lyes in that which is called invention, and in the choice of matter which is the ſtuffe of a diſcourſe. A weake underſtanding is moved with repreſentations, and tragicall deſcriptions, with exclamations, geſtures, and other paſſionate actions: But a man of underſtanding will be inſtructed with reaſons. And this is folly to move the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections without inſtructing the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding; a proceeding contrary to the naturall order which God hath eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed amongſt the faculties of the Soule, and the diſpoſition which the Holy Ghoſt keepes in our ſanctification. The devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which ſuch diſcourſes kindle in the hearers, is a fire of chaffe, which laſts but during the Sermon; But the true inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction which muſt be given to the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, conſiſteth not in vulgar matters. When a Preacher hath ſaid that we muſt believe in God, that every man is a ſinner, that Jeſus Chriſt is come into the world,
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:49144:102"/>and ſhall turne and widen this diſcourſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ith many words, without producing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſuch points any thing, but which is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ady common and knowne to his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tors, I doe not thinke that he hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tucted them. This is not to teach a man, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hen hee is taught but that which hee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nowes already, though one tell it him in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ivers words, and different phraſes. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſt familiar, and moſt notable points for Chriſtians, ſuch as are the Precepts of the Decalogue, and the Articles of the Creed, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nclude an infinite number of rare mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers, ſo that a ſcribe that is knowing in that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hich concernes the Kingdome of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en, may alwaies draw thence new things. The Pſalmiſt who prayed that he might <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e cleare ſighted to diſcover the wonders of the law, knew that it contained much more then moralities naturally knowne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o men. They which treat of the points of religion ſo lightly, preſent you with the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſcall lambe boyled in water, nay even altogether raw, contrary to Gods ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ance. The ordinary excuſe of ſuch Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers,
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:49144:103"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="197" facs="tcp:49144:103"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="198" facs="tcp:49144:104"/>which they put in the eares, and mouth of the common people is this, that they Preach the word of God, and that therefore one ought to content himſelfe with their doctrine, though it be triviall, and one ought not to bee troubled with their frequent repetitions, nor diſdaine their groſſe ſtile, and other defects which are found in their diſcourſes. VVhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto I ſhall onely ſay, that tis an abuſe of the people to ſay, that a mans Sermon is the word of God. It is but the interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation thereof; which if it be defective, or confuſed, or darke, or fooliſh, or extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant, doth injure more the word of God then it receives authority there-from. This colour they give their ignorance, ſerveth to foment that of the people, the greater part whereof content themſelves with that they know of religion, and even make a ſcruple to learne more. One of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipts by which many Preachers are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed to hide this defect is this, to take <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> text of three words, upon which they
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:49144:104"/>inlarge themſelves in digreſſions, mixing all the old and new Teſtament, reducing all divinity into one Sermon, and there is no matter ſo remote from the ſubject, which either by hooke or by crooke they force not to their purpoſe. So that once a valiant expoſitor of Scripture imployed forty yeares in interpreting the Prophet <hi>Eſay.</hi> The prolixity whereby they affect to appeare as Giants who neede a whole Acre of ground to ſtretch themſelves up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is of no great fruict. A ſuccinct, and nervous diſcourſe, nay one ſole reaſon ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry pertinent, or one rare, or extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry conception couched in few words, ſhall rather convert a ſoule, or ſhall grave thereon more lively impreſſions, then theſe vaſt diſcourſes ſhall doe, more fruictfull in words then matter. VVe have many Sermons of Jeſus Chriſt, and ſome of his Apoſtles: But the longeſt of them may be pronounced in the ſpace of halfe an houre. Finally not to touch on the repeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, wherewith many fill their audito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes, we ſhall find them which will be
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:49144:105"/>exact to the dividing of a graine of ſand, by ſo ſmall diſtinctions, and diviſions, that they themſelves can ſcarce diſcerne them. If in lieu of the vulgar method, which un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der colour of deſiring to ſay all that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes a text, yet teacheth nothing but things common and a thouſand times re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated, if a Preacher could find only three, or foure obſervations which are rare, and but little knowne, his auditors might ſay they had learned that which they knew not, And one ſuch Sermon were worth a hundred others: &amp; although the ignorant thinke that this doth much advantage to have a multitude of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, at the end whereof they are as knowing as they were at the beginning. Many alſo have a ſuperſtitious opinion touching Preachers, that one ought not to be more ſought after, or more willingly heard then an other, becauſe all Preach the word of God, and that it is of the ſame weight, and ſame vertue in the mouthes of all. Now tis true that all make profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to carry the ſame ſword of truth, but
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:49144:105"/>all doe not mannage it with the ſame skill, nor with the like force of arme. From whence it comes to paſſe that it cutteth not equally in all hands, nay in many it is, as a plate of leade. Of a thouſand which handle the ſame paſſage of Scripture, it is impoſſible to find two amongſt them which are wholly alike in conceptions, in the order and frame of diſcourſe. In ſo much that repreſenting the ſame ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, they give it ſo divers faces, that even they themſelves are different in ſhape. But thoſe which keepe the reſemblance there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of nearer the life, are to be preferred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore others, which ſhew but the draughts of it groſly delineated.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="202" facs="tcp:49144:106"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>That the words of Scripture had more Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaſis in the mouth of Jeſus Chriſt, and his firſt Diſciples, then they have in ours. The reaſon of this difference.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ITs true that all thoſe to whom Jeſus Chriſt himſelfe Preached when he was converſant upon earth were not conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. The moſt eminent Apoſtles com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained that few perſons received their Preaching; yet nevertheleſſe tis certaine that the word of God had greater efficacy in their mouthes, then now it hath in ours. If it converted not all them who heard it, it made it ſelfe felt by the moſt hardned, as a burning cautery even within the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry entrailes. But beſides, the progreſſe thereof was altogether different. One one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exhortation of St. <hi>Peter</hi> brought in one day three thouſand Jewes to the Church; And by an other Sermon he gained five thouſand ſoules. If at this day wee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the ſame Sermon word by word
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:49144:106"/>in an aſſembly of Jewes, it will not have the ſame ſucceſſe. Although wee ſound the ſame diſcourſe, nay the proper ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe, and formall words, as Jeſus Chriſt, or ſome of his Apoſtles have ſometimes, uttered them, they have not ſuch vertue as they had when they themſelves pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced them <hi>viva voce.</hi> When the Sonne of God ſpeke, there was felt an extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary working and force that never was upon the lipps of mortall man. The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles whom he had animated with his owne vertue, ſpake alſo as out of thunder, and as cherubins of glory. The ſound of their wings was as the noyſe of great wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and as the voice of God Almighty when he ſpeakes. If we would know from whence proceeds ſuch vertue, it may be ſome will ſay it conſiſted rather in their morals then in their words; And that their ſupernaturall works which were ſeene to be done by them were the onely cauſe that rendred their diſcourſe more efficacious, then that of other men; but it appeares to the contrary, by the teſtimony of them
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:49144:107"/>to whom Jeſus Chriſt ſpake in the way to <hi>Emaus,</hi> For although they knew him not, ſo farre were they ſhort of ſeeing any mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle, their heart burned within them, as hee expounded to them the Scriptures. Theſe reaſons may be given hereof; that the Son of God, who knew al the thoughts of his hearers, ſtrucke directly within them; and they could not but be moved, when they heard a voice which ſurprized their moſt ſecret thoughts. That the ſame ſpirit which ſpake in his Diſciples, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched with his words that which men thought was cloſely hid within their hearts: an example in <hi>Ananias,</hi> and <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phira,</hi> whereunto may be referred that we read in the firſt to the <hi>Corinthes</hi> 14.24. and 25. that their breaſt was ful of flames, and the words which came from them lighted as at a fornace, did burne as live ſparks, nay as burning brans. And final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that their tongues were touched imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly with the finger of God, having whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly an other force then ours, which are not touched therewith, but at a diſtance, and by
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:49144:107"/>he interpoſition of many judgements, nay ſeeble, and light.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>What men are moſt hardly ſaved. Of the vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar error which imports that the Paſtors manners edifie aſmuch as his doctrine.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AN antient father ſaid of his time, that in his opinion there were not many Churchmen, or Paſtors that were ſaved. This may ſeeme ſtrange. But if we may ſay there are men for whom it is difficult to be ſaved, they are thoſe which have the charge of ſoules. For to ſave themſelves, they ought to ſave many others. For whom it ſufficeth not to have piety, and other vertues which are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to all other Chriſtians. Their is need of knowledge, and eloquence. The want of morall vertues (which alwayes render it more criminall) repugneth not the eſſence of his office, nor abateth the
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:49144:108"/>dignity of the Sacraments, nor the efficacy of the word which he adminiſtreth. Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance is the moſt formall crime of him who ought to inſtruct others. A good man may be a bad Paſtor. The vulgar hold for a maxime, That the good life of a Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher edifieth as much, or more then his doctrine. This error is truely popular, and more fooliſh then can be imagined. Its true that workes ought to accompany words, and woe to that man who practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth not his owne doctrine. But this is impiety to thinke that the actions of a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor are more conſiderable, more perfect, or of greater edification then his doctrine which is the rule; which is more eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all to his charge, more fruictfull in inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, more neceſſary to ſalvation, either the ſeeing of his example, or the hearing his word? Is the example of a man of greater weight them the Ordinance of God? Is it from the Paſtors example that wee receive the faith, or from his Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching? Are his good works the power of God to ſalvation? Doe they containe the
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:49144:108"/>remiſſion of our ſins? Shall we be ſaved by them or by his doctrine? He which finds more efficacy in a mans example then in the word of Jeſus Chriſt is not worthy to be his Diſciple.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>That it is more profitable for us to be taught by men then by Angels. Why the world va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lues not prophets, but after their death.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MAny could wiſh they might bee taught by Angels, thinking that their inſtructions will be more profitable, and their word more efficacious. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they are deceived. For there are divers points whereof the Angels cannot ſpeake with ſo great feeling, nor with a know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge ſo particular as men. The diſeaſes of the body, and other kinds of the croſſe, the burthen of ſinne, the terrors of conſcience, the horrors of death, the combate of the fleſh againſt the ſpirit, repentance it ſelf,
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:49144:109"/>and regeneration, are things whereof they have no experience, and therefore cannot be touched with ſuch compaſſion towards ſinners, as men who feele the ſame infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities. This is a reaſon why the ſonne of God would take upon him our infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, to the end hee might have the more compaſſion, and ſpeake with greater effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy; furthermore that Angell which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to <hi>Cornelius</hi> the Centurion, would not undertake to inſtruct him, but ſent him for this purpoſe to a ſinfull mortall man. This is the cuſtome of the world, and examples thereof are frequent in all ages, to undervalue, or even perſecute Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets while they live, and to adore them after death. The reaſon is, that the eye of the fleſh ſeeth in them the ſame viſage as in other men, the ſame naturall infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and a contemptible appearance; eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially if he be in his owne country, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midſt his familiars. <hi>Saul</hi> asked <hi>Samuel,</hi> whether he was a man of God, not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that he was ſo, becauſe he ſaw nothing extraordinary in his perſon. The bald
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:49144:109"/>head of <hi>Eliſhai</hi> ſerved as an object of moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kery to the little children. Many that loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked on St. <hi>Paul</hi> as abſent, ſaid that his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence had not ſo much force as his wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings. On the other ſide, the moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent ſervants of God, are they againſt whom Satan hath prepared moſt ambu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes. The liberty of their cenſures ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders them odious. He that reverenced ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterday <hi>Iohn</hi> the Baptiſt, willingly procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his impriſonment, or death; but after that God had taken them into his reſt, and that there was nothing remaining but the ſound of their voice, which ſeemeth to eccho ſtill in their graves, the world re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gretts at what it hath loſt, and endeavours to expiate its ingratitude with exceſſive honours. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> was accuſed of adultery, condemned, chaſed out of his Church, and confined in baniſhment, where finally hee dyed. The children of them which had driven him away fell downe on their knees before the dead bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and deſired pardon of it for their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents. Such alſo have builded rich tombs
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:49144:110"/>in memory of the juſt, who had perſecuted them in their lives. Great were the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages of them who were converſant with the ſonne of God, who might heare him ſpeaking with open mouth, propoſe unto him the moſt difficult doubts, and queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and learne from his mouth an infinite number of ſublime, and unheard-of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines. But they payd him with outrages; and many honour him at this day, who would have helped to have crucified him, if they had bin in his time.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>The want of particular inſtructions.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ALL the inſtruction which is ſought for at this day from the mouth of Preachers, is reduced to Sermons. The moſt excellent amongſt them, out of the pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit, is no more then a private man in the judgement of the vulgar. The common people believe that publique inſtructions
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:49144:110"/>are ſufficient for them; and as for the reſt every Chriſtian may order his actions ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as they conform to them. There is none ſo ſottiſhly ignorant who doth not think himſelfe capable to direct his owne conſcience. Notwithſtanding mans life is full of occurrents, wherein the wiſeſt are ſubject to deceive themſelves; and the moſt conſcientious, by truſting over much to their owne judgement, commit notable faults in the conduct of their affairs, of houſhold government, or trading, of judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cature, of publique policy, and other voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Witneſſe <hi>Davids</hi> heedleſneſſe, in cauſing the Arke to bee carryed upon his owne Chariot. Moreover publique in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions cannot expreſſe ſo many cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances which often change the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of actions. And which is more, not onely the points which lye in practiſe, but alſo thoſe which concern meerely beliefe, being compoſed in publique, frame not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes in the mind of the hearers ſo exact an impreſſion, as particular inſtruction; auricular confeſſion, if it had not paſſed
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:49144:111"/>into ſuperſtition, was an exerciſe of great profit.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. X. <hi>Of books of religion, and of the time imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in them to the prejudice of Scripture. Of the multitude, vanity, kinds and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of them.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AMongſt the abuſes which keepe up the ignorance of the vulgar, wee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt alſo the reading of ſo many religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous books, whereunto the common peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple give their time, and thoughts, as to an exerciſe of great edification, although the books of a good divine containe in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance the ſame matters which are in Scripture. Whoſoever ſhall read in <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen,</hi> or <hi>Nazianzene,</hi> the ſacrifice of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> curiouſly painted out with all its cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, with a repreſentation as pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theticke as Rhetoricke can furniſh it with, ſhal never be ſo lively touched there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:49144:111"/>as by the ſimple recitall of <hi>Moyſes.</hi> A paraphraſe of the new Teſtament, is but a dead Letter, in compariſon of the viva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of the Text. All this is ſaid without derogating from the merit of ſo many learned pens, ancient and moderne, which have travelled to ſet us at eaſe. Their works have converted many ſouls; the writing of a man powerfull in ſpirit, preach, as well as his voice. But this eulo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie appertains not to all them who un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake to write; And all the authors, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven thoſe which are worth the reading, are not for the vulgar. Beſides the books which may ſerve to inſtruct the common people, are made hurtfull by their quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. The number is become ſo exorbitant, and ſtill multiplyed daily in ſuch abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, that the greater part of Chriſtians imploye ten times as much time in this reading, as in that of the Bible. That fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Doctor <hi>Luther</hi> had in hatred his own books, and wiſhed that they were buried, for feare the readers ſhould ſpend that time in them they ought in the Scripture.
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:49144:112"/>I am not of their opinion who regret the loſſe of ſo many books of the ancient fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and other writings which time hath cauſed to vaniſh. On the contrary, I think that this loſſe is a great gaine to us, and a diſcharge of many unprofitable burthens. The naturall hiſtory dictated by <hi>Solomon,</hi> and divers other writings mentioned in Scripture it ſelfe, were never loſt without the particular providence of God, which would not that his Church ſhould bee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercharged with ſo many volumes. Of all the Apoſtles there are but ſix whoſe writings have bin preſerved; and yet it is certaine that the other Apoſtles were no leſſe carefull to write to their flocks: Nay it is credible that thoſe whoſe Epiſtles we have writ, many others, which the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God hath ſuppreſſed. Jeſus Chriſt himſelfe, writ not, nor would that all his miracles ſhould be comprized in the hiſtory, leſt their prolixity ſhould ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede the meaſure of our life, and the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity of our memory.</p>
               <p>The reading the fathers is not a taske of
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:49144:112"/>the vulgar. To underſtand them, you muſt know the hiſtory of their times. There occur in this field an infinite number of particulars, and matters which ſerve for no uſe at this day, and even many which are full of thornes, which the common peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple cannot handle without pricking them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the blood. If the fruicts which are found ſcattered in this vaſt extenſion of the fathers were collected a part, and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped together in one volume, this abridge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment would be of great profit. But we are to ſpeake of moderne Writers, the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude whereof is prodigious.</p>
               <p>Many books are reputed learned, which are more filld with word then matter. If from all the books in divinity which goe up and downe the world, there be taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the repetitions, the amplifications, the ſuperfluous allegations, and a million of intire volumes great and ſmall which declare nothing, but what ſo many others have ſaid before, the reſidue will be very few. One may ſay of the greateſt part of them, that whoſoever hath read one, hath
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:49144:113"/>read them all. There are alwayes the ſame conceptions, the ſame reaſons; ſaving that the words are different. That which one calls dirt, the other nameth dung. Where they differ onely in the order, tranſpoſing what others have ſaid, and diſguiſing it with other tranſiſions, conjunctions, or with ſome pleaſing point. All this with a new title makes men think that this booke is altogether new. The world is full of writers, and there is not a pedant which will not be one. For ſo that a man fill up much paper, this is enough to get a great reputation. I know one that to attaine to this, uſed the following method, which is common to him with many others. To make a treatiſe, of controverſie, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary (which is at this day as a bridge for aſſes) he had upon the table five or ſixe divers authors, tooke one line from one, and another from an other, and beating all together, then adding thereto ſome He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew word tranſcribed out of the Dictio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, and a long thrid of paſſages out of the fathers, made a compoſition, upon
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:49144:113"/>which he wrote his name; And the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant ſaid behold the Commentaryes of N. upon the Pſalmes, or upon ſome of the ſmaller Prophets. It were a great good for the publique that none ſhould write, but he that had very rare conceptions, or ſo little common that they might be held for new. One onely extraordinary obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation comprehended in ten or twelve lines, is more worth then all the great tomes out of which nothing that is new can be learned.</p>
               <p>All the books that can be written in divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, are either doctrinall, or morall, or hiſtoricall, or of prophecie, or of contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie, or mixed and compoſed of all theſe together, or of many of them. The forme whereof is divers; Commentaryes, common places, meditations, formes of prayer, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milyes, diſcourſes of vertues, and vices, and the like particular treatiſe. As for controverſies I have thereof ſaid my opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Alſo for commentaryes, two or three for the moſt part ſuffiſe, taken from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the reſt, who for the moſt part
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:49144:114"/>have more of Grammar then divinity, and ſound of nothing but repetitions. The ſame choice is neceſſary amongſt authors which handle all Religion heaped together in a body. Amongſt ſo many bookes of meditations, there are ſcarce two which containe any rarity. There are ſeene ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny words ſet out to ſay that which the world knoweth already well enough. There is likewiſe a great multitude of Sermons which run from hand to hand. The vulgar often admire Preachers, who putting what they ſay in writing, you ſhall find that they have ſaid nothing ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary. We have ſeene Homilies dictated by great perſonages, in whom be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide the wide, and rampant ſtyle, you meete with even childiſh diſcourſes; but the world will be deceived. The expoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon the decalogue, the Creed, and Lords Prayer, are the ſubject of infinite treatyes wherein you ſhall ſcarcely find a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing, but repetitions from ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and matters very common. As for formes of prayer fitted to particulars,
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:49144:114"/>although their ayme be rather to frame a Chriſtians practiſe in this exerciſe, then to give him inſtruction, if it appertaines not to all to give their conceptions for rules, and preſcribe the forme, and words an other ought to uſe in ſpeaking to God. But furthermore, they which ſpend all their time in this kind of reading, ſhall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide alwaies in an ignorant devotion.</p>
               <p>This would be an ineſtimable good, if inſtead of ſo many volumes which ſteale away the greateſt part of our life, we had a collection of the rareſt ſecrets in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, ſeparated from all vulgar matters, and freed from all theſe maſſes of words. Such a worke would teach us more in one day, then ſo many others could doe in an age. I ſhall willingly ſubſcribe to their adviſe who have ſaid that this would bee the richeſt piece that hath bin put out ſince the Apoſtles time. Its true that thoſe have not obſerved the true field from whence theſe matters muſt be taken, but it is eaſie to be found.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="220" facs="tcp:49144:115"/>
               <head>CHAP. XI. <hi>Great knowledge lieth not in the quantity of matters, but in their quality. The title of great divines given faſly to many.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BY the common voice, that man is held for a great divine, who knowes the languages neceſſary to this profeſſion; who underſtands Philoſophie, who hath read the fathers, and can relate what they thought upon every point of religion; who is verſed in Eccleſiaſticall Hiſtory; who is ready in controverſies, in ſchoole di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctions and ſubtilities, beſides the exact knowledge of common places which are in uſe, bordured with texts of Scripture, and ſtuft with other allegations. But all theſe qualities together cannot make a great Divine but in reputation. This is truly a great advantage to heare the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and God himſelfe in the ſame lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage wherein they ſpake. 'Tis certaine that the Scripture is pure, and more em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaticke
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:49144:115"/>in its originall tongues, then in any tranſlation. But the onely knowledge of tongues ſupplyes but a Grammaticall underſtanding, wherein many Jewes and Greeks may excel, without deſerving the title of Divines. Good ſtore of Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie ſufficeth not; though a good Divine ought to be a good Philoſopher. To know what <hi>Tertull.</hi> ſaid, or what was St. <hi>Auſtins</hi> opinion, is not of the very eſſence of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity; ſo much doth it come ſhort of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the higeſt degree thereof. Many that lived before all theſe fathers were in the world, ceaſed not to be as great Divines as they which have employed at this day thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty yeares in this reading of the fathers. The ſame is of Hiſtory. Before the ſubject thereof was in the world, Divinity was compleate. A man endowed with memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, who can tell what bereſies have reig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, what orders were made in ſuch coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, what diſputes or diverſities have aroſe in Church Policie, &amp;c. may bee held knowing in Hiſtory; But this is follie to hold him in this reſpect, for an eminent
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:49144:116"/>Divine. The knowledge of controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, is accidental, and embraceth not all the dimenſions of Religion. The knowledge of the moſt ſubtile points of Divinity re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to the forme of art, a promptuary of ordinary paſſages, and arguments upon all kinds of ſubjects, are not ſufficient neither to give us a great Divine. The idea there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of belongs to another diſcourſe; whence we may learne That extraordinary know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge conſiſteth not ſo much in the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of matters, as in the rarity of them.</p>
               <p>I will now conclude this treatiſe of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular Errors, that I may paſſe to a higher ſubject, and aſſay after this offering of goates haire, to preſent you with ſcarlet for the ornament of the Sanctuary. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
